좋습니다.
Cool.
여러분 안녕하세요.
CME 295에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
Hello everyone, and
welcome to CME 295--
이 강의는 트랜스포머와
대규모 언어모델을 다룹니다.
Transformers and
Large Language Models.
저는 Afshine입니다.
So my name is Afshine.
그리고 이 강의는 Shervine과 함께
진행할 예정입니다.
And I will be teaching
this class with Shervine,
Shervine은 뒤쪽에 있습니다.
who's in the back.
본격적으로 시작하기 전에
먼저 저희를 소개하겠습니다.
And before I start, I'm just
going to introduce ourselves.
저희는 쌍둥이 형제이고,
So we're twin brothers,
and we actually
비슷한 배경을 가지고 있습니다.
had a similar background.
둘 다 프랑스에 있는
Centrale Paris라는 학교를 나왔고
So we both went to
a school in France
그 이후부터는 각자의 길을 갔습니다.
called Centrale Paris, and
then we each went our way.
저는 MIT로 갔고,
Shervine은
So on my end, I went to
MIT, and then Shervine
Stanford에서 ICME 석사 과정을 밟았습니다.
went to Stanford to do
the ICME Master's program.
그리고 그 이후부터는
업계 경력도 굉장히 비슷합니다.
And after that, I guess
our industry background
저희의 업계 경험도 매우 유사합니다.
is very similar as well.
저는 먼저 Uber에 갔고,
So I first went
to Uber, and then
Shervine도 Uber에 합류했고,
Shervine came to Uber
as well, and then
그 후 Shervine이 Google로 갔고,
저도 Google에서 일했습니다.
Shervine left to Google,
and I went to Google.
그리고 최근에는 제가 Netflix에 합류했고,
And then very recently,
I joined Netflix,
Shervine도 Netflix에 들어왔습니다.
and Shervine joined
Netflix as well.
저희는 대규모 언어모델 관련 업무를 해왔습니다.
And we've been working
on Large Language Models.
그래서 저희는 기술적인 배경을 가지고 있고,
So yeah, I guess we have
technical backgrounds,
주로 LLM 분야에 집중해 왔습니다.
and mostly oriented
towards LLMs.
자, 그럼 왜 이 강의를 하게 되었을까요?
OK, so why are we
doing this class?
2020년부터 Shervine과 저는
NLP 분야를 집중적으로 연구해 왔습니다.
So since 2020, Shervine and I
have been specializing in NLP.
그리고 그동안 이 강좌를
워크샵 형식으로 진행해왔습니다.
And we've been giving this class
in the format of a workshop that
매년 한 번씩 열렸던 워크샵이었습니다.
was done on a yearly basis.
2021년, 2022년, 2023년, 2024년에도 진행했고,
2022년에는 ChatGPT가 등장했죠.
So in 2021, 2022, 2023,
2024, ChatGPT came in 2022,
그리고 갑자기 LLM에 대한
관심이 크게 높아졌습니다.
and suddenly there was a
lot of interest for LLMs.
그래서 실제로 저희가
이 강의를 정규 과목으로 개설한 것은 지난 봄입니다.
And so it's actually
last spring that we
이 강의를 Stanford 정규 수업으로 처음 개설하게 되었습니다.
started to offer this
class as a Stanford course
지금은 CME 295라는 이름으로 진행되고 있고, 이번이 두 번째입니다.
that is now called CME 295, and
this is the second instance.
좋습니다.
Cool.
그럼 이 강의에서 무엇을 기대할 수 있을까요?
So what can you expect
from this class?
무엇보다도, 이제 LLM은 거의 모든 곳에 사용되고 있습니다.
So first of all, LLMs are
basically everywhere now.
여기서 저희의 목표는 두 가지입니다.
And I guess our goal
here is twofold.
첫 번째는 이러한 기술이 어떻게 동작하는지,
So the first one is to learn
about the underlying mechanism
근본적인 메커니즘을 배우는 것입니다.
that makes all this work.
이제 트랜스포머에 대해 살펴보겠습니다.
And we're going to see
the transformer, which
트랜스포머는 이러한 모든 기술의 기반이 되는 아키텍처입니다.
is the foundational architecture
that makes all this work.
그리고 두 번째로는, LLM이 어떻게 학습되고
And then the second thing is to
know how these LLMs are trained
어디에 적용되는지 알아보는 것입니다.
and where they are applied.
혹시 아직도 이 강의가 자신에게 맞는지
So in case you're
still wondering
고민하고 있다면, 말씀드리고 싶습니다.
if this class is
good for you, I would
이 강의는 이 분야에 전반적으로 관심 있는 분들에게
say that this class is great
for people who just in general
아주 좋은 강의입니다. 예를 들어,
have an interest in this field,
either because you wanted
이 분야를 커리어 목표로 삼고 싶거나,
to make it your career goal,
if you want to be a research
연구원이나 머신러닝 과학자가 되고 싶거나,
scientist or an ML scientist,
or if you want to develop
LLM을 활용한 개인 프로젝트를 개발하고 싶은 분들,
a personal project that
relies on LLMs to some extent,
혹은 실제로 어떤 점에서 주의가 필요한지,
to just knowing the
caveats, I guess what works,
어떤 것이 잘 되고 어떤 것은 잘 안 되는지 알고 싶거나,
what doesn't, or just say if
you're in a separate field
혹은 다른 분야에 있지만 AI, 생성형 AI, LLM이
and you just want to know how
this whole AI, GenAI, LLMs
어떻게 동작하는지, 그리고 자신의 분야에 어떻게 적용할 수 있는지
thing works and how you can
apply it to your domain.
이제 선수 지식에 대해 말씀드리겠습니다.
So now in terms
of prerequisites,
최소한으로 필요한 것은
I would say that
at a very minimum
기본적인 머신러닝 지식입니다.
you should have some
foundations in ML,
예를 들어, 모델이 어떻게 학습되는지,
like basically know how
a model is trained, what
신경망이 무엇인지, 그리고 선형대수의 기초를 알고 있어야 합니다.
a neural network is, and also
some basics in linear algebra,
예를 들어, 행렬 곱셈이 어떻게 이루어지는지 정도는 기본적으로 알아야 합니다.
so basically how matrices
are multiplied, for instance.
하지만 아직 이 분야의 역량을 개발 중이라도
But even if you have
a developing, I guess,
이 분야에 대한 기본 역량만 갖추고 있어도 괜찮습니다.
competency in this
field, I guess it's fine,
저희가 계속 도와드릴 테니 걱정하지 않으셔도 됩니다.
we're still be here
to help you out.
이게 바로 이상적인 선수 과목이라고 보시면 됩니다.
But I guess this is like the
ideal set of prerequisites.
좋습니다.
Cool.
운영 관련 안내를 계속해서 드리자면, 이 수업은 매주
So still on the logistics, so
this class will be held every
금요일 3시 30분부터 5시 20분까지 이곳에서 진행됩니다.
Friday from 3:30 to 5:20,
and it will be held here.
이 수업은 2학점짜리 강의입니다.
So this class is two units.
성적은 등급(letter grade)으로 받을 수도 있고,
And you have the choice to
either take it as a letter
혹은 패스/논패스(credit/non-credit)로 들을 수도 있습니다.
or a credit/non-credit.
보시면 아시겠지만, 수업은 이렇게 준비되어 있고
So as you could
tell from the setup,
강의는 녹화되고 있습니다.
we're basically
recording this class.
혹시 이 시간에 참석이 어려운 분들은
And if you cannot for some
reason attend this time,
Shervine과 협의해서 녹화본을 받을 수 있도록 하겠습니다.
this slot, we'll make sure with
Shervine to make the recordings
녹화본은 금요일 밤이나,
토요일에 업로드할 예정입니다.
available, either tonight,
like every Friday night,
혹은 토요일에 올라갈 수 있습니다.
or on Saturday.
성적 산정에 대해 말씀드리면,
So in terms of the
grades, so what
이번 쿼터에는 총 두 번의 시험이 예정되어 있습니다.
we're doing for this quarter
is to have two exams.
하나는 중간고사로,
So one is the
midterm, which will
다섯 번째 수업(10월 24일)에 진행될 예정입니다.
be happening during our fifth
instance, which is October 24.
두 번째 시험은 기말고사로,
And then the second exam
will be the final exam,
12월 8일이 속한 주에 치러질 예정입니다.
which will be held in
the week of December 8.
정확한 날짜는 추후 공지하겠습니다.
So date is still TBD.
확정되면 알려드리겠습니다.
So we'll let you know.
좋습니다.
Cool.
매번 강의가 끝나면 슬라이드와 녹화본을
So every time we
have a lecture, we'll
웹사이트에 업로드할 예정입니다.
be posting the slides and the
recordings on the website.
혹시 관심 있으신 분들을 위해,
And in case you're
interested, we also
홈페이지에 강의 계획서도 올려두었습니다.
have the syllabus
in there, so you
어떤 주제를 다룰 예정인지 미리 확인하실 수 있습니다.
can know a little bit what
are the topics that we'll
미리 어떤 내용을 다룰지 확인하실 수 있습니다.
be talking about.
그리고 교재로는 이 Super Study Guide,
즉 'Transformer LLMs' 책을 사용합니다.
And the class textbook is
this Super Study Guide--
'Transformer LLMs'가 교재입니다.
Transformer LLMs.
여기에 책 한 권이 준비되어 있으니,
원하시면 잠깐 살펴보셔도 됩니다.
So we have a copy here in
case you want to take a look.
강의에서 다루는 주요 개념들은
이 책에도 거의 다 담겨 있습니다.
So yeah, I guess a
lot of the concepts
그래서 이 수업의 많은 내용이
책에서도 확인하실 수 있습니다.
that we have in this class
will actually be in the book.
따라서 책을 참고하면서 따라가면
많이 도움이 될 겁니다.
So I guess it's a helpful
way to follow this as well.
그리고 이 강의를 아주 짧고 간단하게
요약한 버전도 만들었습니다.
And also, we did some very
short, condensed version
이름하여 VIP 치트시트인데,
전체 강의 내용을 압축한 자료입니다.
of this whole class that we
called the VIP cheat sheet.
이 치트시트는 GitHub에서
다운받으실 수 있습니다.
So this one is
available on GitHub
관심 있으시면 참고하셔도 좋습니다.
in case you're interested.
그리고 이 치트시트는 현재
여러 언어로도 번역되어 있습니다.
And yeah, we also translated it
into a number of languages now.
혹시 여러분의 언어가 없다면 알려주세요.
By the way, if your language
is not there, let us know,
언제든 같이 번역 작업을
진행할 수 있습니다.
and happy to work on
that as well together.
네, 좋습니다.
OK, cool.
이제 운영 관련해서 남은 안내는
마지막인 것 같습니다.
I think it's the last things
on the logistics part.
각종 공지사항은 Canvas에
게시할 예정입니다.
So in terms of
announcements, we'll
Canvas에서 확인해 주세요.
be posting things on Canvas.
혹시 질문이 있으면
언제든 연락 주셔도 됩니다.
In case you have
any questions, you
언제든 저희에게 문의하실 수 있습니다.
can of course reach out to us.
또한 Canvas에는 Ed라는 탭이 있어서,
But there is also a tab on
Canvas that's called Ed.
아마 이미 익숙하실 겁니다.
I'm sure you're familiar.
Ed 탭을 클릭하고,
질문을 올려주시면 됩니다.
So you just click on that,
just post your question,
그러면 Shervine과 제가 답변드리겠습니다.
and then Shervine and
I will be responding.
저희에게 연락하실 때는 메일링 리스트가 있고,
And I guess to reach out to
us, you have this mailing list.
저희가 둘뿐이라, 편하게
연락주시면 됩니다.
Or we're just two,
so just ding us.
좋습니다.
Cool.
운영 관련해서 궁금한 점 있으신가요?
So on the logistics, do we
have any questions so far?
그리고 한 가지 더 말씀드리면,
And one thing I
forgot to mention
이 강의가 녹화되고 있기 때문에,
is that, given that we're
recording this class,
여러분이 질문하실 때는,
I guess if you're
asking a question,
여러분이 질문하면, 영상을 보는 분들 입장에서는
it may not be super
clear for the viewer what
어떤 질문인지 명확하게 전달되지 않을 수 있습니다.
your question was.
그래서 여러분의 질문을 제가 반복해서 말해주려고 합니다.
So I'm going to make an effort
to just repeat your question.
조금 어색할 수도 있지만, 최대한 잊지 않고 하려고 할게요.
It will sound weird, but I'll
try to not forget, but yeah.
여기까지 진행 관련해서 혹시 질문 있으신가요?
So any questions so
far on the logistics?
네.
Yeah.
질문은 시험에 코딩 문제가 포함되어 있는지에 대한 내용이었습니다.
So the question is whether there
are coding parts in the exams.
답은, 코딩 문제는 없습니다.
So the answer is no.
시험은 수업에서 다룬 개념에만 집중할 예정입니다.
So the exams will
purely focus on concepts
즉, 수업에서 본 내용과 개념이 시험 범위죠.
that we see in class.
그리고 시험이 여러분을 일부러 어렵게 하려는 목적은 아닙니다.
And actually, it's
not meant to trap you.
강의를 잘 따라오셨다면
So I guess if you
follow the class, if you
수업에서 보여지는 슬라이드와 개념만 잘 챙기면 충분할 겁니다.
see the slides and the concepts
that we see, should be fine.
네.
Yeah.
아, 네.
Oh, yeah.
질문은, 대기자 명단에 있으면 어떻게 해야 하냐는 내용이었습니다.
Question is, if you're
waitlisted, what do you do?
제 경험상, 많은 분들이 학기 초에
I think, so by experience,
a lot of people
시간표를 정리하게 됩니다.
will finalize their schedule.
수강을 취소하는 분도 있고, 그대로 듣는 분도 있죠.
Some people will
drop, some won't.
혹시 여전히 대기자라면, 저희에게 말씀해 주세요.
In case you're still
waitlisted, come talk to us.
하지만 지금 대기 인원이 6명이라
But I'm pretty
confident it's going
아마 곧 수강이 가능해질 거라고 생각합니다.
to be OK, because I think the
waitlist right now is six.
너무 걱정 안 하셔도 될 것 같습니다.
So, I think it should be fine.
좋아요.
Cool.
네.
Yeah.
슬라이드는 웹사이트에 올라갈 예정이고,
They will be on the
website, and we'll
Canvas에도 링크를 게시할 예정입니다.
make sure to also
post a link on Canvas.
네.
Yeah.
방금 질문은 슬라이드가 어디 있느냐는 내용이었습니다.
So the question was,
where are the slides.
슬라이드는 웹사이트에 있습니다.
And they're on the website.
좋아요, 네.
Cool, yeah.
다음 질문은 시험의 배점에 관한 것입니다.
So question is on the
weighting of the exams.
이 강의는 과제가 없습니다.
So there is no homework.
중간고사 50%, 기말고사 50%로 점수가 나뉩니다.
So 50% is midterm, 50% is final.
그리고 성적에는...
And no grades--
다른 요소의 가중치는 없습니다.
I mean, no weights
are from that.
특히, 만약 이 시간대와 겹치는 일정이 있다면
And particular, I
mean if this slot
이 강의는 녹화되고 있다는 점을 기억하세요.
is conflicting with
something, just keep in mind
혹시 수업에 참석하지 못하셔도 괜찮습니다.
that we are recording this.
그래서 꼭 참석하지 않아도 됩니다.
So it's fine if you cannot
attend this session.
네.
Yeah.
네? 다시 말씀해 주실래요?
Sorry?
아, 질문이 기말고사 범위에 대한 건가요?
Oh, is the question
that the final
기말고사가 강의 뒷부분만을 다루는지에 관한 질문이군요.
is about just the second
half of the class?
아직 시험은 작성하지 않았지만,
We have not written
the exam yet,
그 부분에 대해서 고민 중입니다.
but I think this is
something we are thinking of.
아마도 기말고사는 강의 후반부 내용이 주가 될 것 같습니다.
So the final is probably going
to be about the second half
그쪽 주제들 위주로요.
of the topics.
좋습니다.
Cool.
정리하면, 중간고사 50%, 기말고사 50%입니다.
OK, long story short, 50%
midterm, 50% final exam.
그리고 이 강의는 재미있을 거예요.
And it's a fun class.
좋아요.
Cool.
이제 본격적으로 강의를 시작하겠습니다.
So with that, I'm going to
just slowly start the class.
그리고 한 가지 더 말씀드리고 싶은 점이 있습니다.
So another thing that
I want to mention
우리가 어떤 내용을 다룰 때마다
was every time we're
talking about something,
슬라이드 하단에 출처가 표시될 겁니다.
you will see that at
the bottom of the slide
이 출처는 주로 인용을 명확히 하기 위한 것이고,
there will be a source, and
it's mostly for-- so first,
여러분이 좀 더 자료를 찾아보고 싶을 때 도움이 될 거예요.
to credits, whatever,
we're quoting, but also
혹시 더 관심이 있으신 분들은
for you to dig into
those materials a bit
추가적으로 참고하시면 됩니다.
more in case you're interested.
왜냐하면, 당연히 저희는 일주일에 두 시간밖에 없고,
Because, of course, we have
only two hours per week,
총 9주에서 10주 정도밖에 시간이 없습니다.
and we only have
nine or 10 weeks,
그래서 모든 내용을 다 다루기에는 시간이 턱없이 부족합니다.
so there's nowhere near enough
time for us to cover everything.
그리고 두 번째로 말씀드릴 점은,
And the second disclaimer is
you will see that the field is
이 분야에는 약어가 정말 많다는 것입니다.
full of abbreviations.
저 역시 처음에는 이런 약어들이 굉장히 낯설고 두려웠습니다.
So I myself was completely
scared of them when I started.
하지만 이 수업이 끝날 때쯤에는,
But hopefully by the
end of the class,
여러분 모두 이 약어들이 무엇을 의미하는지
you will have a
mental mapping of what
머릿속에 맵처럼 정리되어 있을 거라고 기대합니다.
these abbreviations
mean, respect
즉, 각 약어가 어떤 개념을 가리키는지 알게 될 것입니다.
to what they correspond to.
그래서 수업 마지막에 이런 맵이 생긴다면,
So yes, so if you
have a mental mapping
저희가 수업을 잘 했다는 뜻이겠죠.
towards the end of the class,
then we know e did a good job.
그럼 이제 본격적으로 시작해보겠습니다.
So with that, let's start.
먼저 큰 그림부터 살펴보려고 하는데요,
And I guess we will start at
a very high level, because I
아마 대부분이 처음부터 시작한다고 생각하고
will just assume that I guess
we're starting from scratch.
가장 기초적인 NLP 이야기를 먼저 하겠습니다.
And we're going to talk
about NLP in general.
NLP가 오늘 배우는 첫 번째 약어가 될 텐데요,
So NLP is going to be
our first abbreviation.
NLP는 자연어처리(Natural Language Processing)를 의미합니다.
So NLP stands for Natural
Language Processing.
이 분야는 주로 텍스트를 다루고,
And it is a field that is
around manipulating text,
텍스트로 여러 작업을 수행하는 것을 목표로 합니다.
just computing things with text.
아주 큰 틀에서 보면, NLP의 문제들은
And at a very high level, can
basically classify NLP tasks
크게 세 가지 범주로 나눌 수 있습니다.
into three buckets.
첫 번째 범주는 바로 분류(classification)입니다.
So the first bucket is what
we call classification.
즉, 입력 텍스트가 주어졌을 때,
So we have an input
text as an input.
우리가 원하는 것은 어떤 값을 예측하는 것입니다.
And then what we want
is to predict something.
예를 들어 영화 리뷰가 있다고 할 때,
So one example is you
have a movie review
그 리뷰의 감성이 긍정인지, 부정인지,
and you want to predict whether
the sentiment is positive,
아니면 중립인지 예측하는 것이죠.
negative, or neutral.
이것이 분류의 한 예시입니다.
So that's one example.
또 다른 예시로는 의도(intent) 파악이 있습니다.
You can also have intent
detection, just knowing
예를 들어, 그 사람이 무엇을 하려고 하는지 알아내는 작업도 있습니다.
what, for instance,
the person wants to do.
예를 들어, '내일 알람을 설정하고 싶다'라고 말할 때를 생각해봅시다.
So let's suppose you say, I want
to create an alarm for tomorrow.
이 경우의 의도는 '알람 생성'이 되는 것이죠.
So the intent here
is create an alarm.
또한 언어를 판별하는 작업도 있습니다.
So also to detect a
language-- so for instance,
예를 들어, 어떤 글이 프랑스어로 작성되었는지 판별하는 것이죠.
if you write among
French, you want
그리고 토픽 모델링 같은 작업도 있습니다.
to detect that text is in
French, topic modeling.
두 번째 범주는 우리가 멀티 분류라고 부르는 작업입니다.
The second category is what
we call multi-classification.
여전히 텍스트를 입력으로 사용하지만,
So we still have
a text as input,
이번에는 한 가지가 아니라 여러 가지를 예측하는 경우입니다.
but this time we predict
more than one thing.
이 범주에는 다양한 과제들이 포함됩니다.
So you have a number of
tasks in that bucket as well.
가장 대표적인 예로는 개체명 인식, 즉 Named Entity Recognition이 있습니다.
So one that is very popular is
called Named Entity Recognition,
줄여서
a.k.a.
NER이라고 부르기도 하죠.
NER.
이 과제는 입력 텍스트가 주어졌을 때,
So what that task does
is, given an input text,
특정 단어에 라벨을 지정하는 작업입니다.
we want to basically label
some specific words, like,
예를 들면, 어떤 것이 장소인지,
for instance, identifying
whether something
시간인지 등으로 식별하는 것이죠.
is a location, or
a time, and so on.
또한 이 외에도 다양한 과제들이 있습니다.
And then you have some
other tasks as well
조금 더 언어학적인 접근을 하는 과제들도 있는데요,
that are a little bit more
on the linguistic side.
요즘에는 다소 인기가 줄었지만,
I think they're less
trendy now, but I
10년 전쯤에는 많이 연구되던 분야입니다.
guess 10 years ago
it was something
대표적으로 품사 태깅이 있습니다.
that people would study a lot.
이는 단어가 명사인지,
So part of speech tagging, which
is about just figuring out which
동사인지 등을 파악하는 작업입니다.
word is a noun, a
verb, et cetera,
또는 구문 분석 관련 과제들도 있는데요, 의존 구문 분석이나 구성 구문 분석 등이 있습니다.
or some parsing-related tasks,
so dependency or constituency
이런 parsing 작업들이 있습니다.
parsing.
그리고 마지막으로, 요즘 매우 인기 있는 범주가 있습니다.
And then the last bucket, which
is very popular these days is
바로 생성(generation) 과제입니다.
the generation bucket.
이 경우에는 입력도 텍스트이고,
So you have the text
as input, and you also
출력도 텍스트가 됩니다.
have text as output.
그리고 이 경우에는 출력의 길이가
다양할 수 있습니다.
And here the length
can be variable,
즉, 출력 텍스트의 길이를
미리 알 수 없다는 뜻입니다.
meaning you don't know what
the length of your output text
사전에 출력의 길이가 정해져 있지 않아요.
will be beforehand.
여기에도 여러 가지 과제가 있습니다.
So here you have several tasks.
예를 들어, 기계 번역이 있죠.
So for instance, you
have machine translation.
예를 들어, 영어로 된 문장을
독일어로 번역하고 싶다고 해봅시다.
So for instance,
something in English and I
영어 문장을 독일어로 번역하는 예시입니다.
wanted to let's say German.
또한 질문 응답도
대표적인 작업입니다.
Question answering--
so typically
여러분이 사용하는 ChatGPT나 Gemini 같은 어시스턴트가
바로 이런 질문 응답을 수행합니다.
the ChatGPT, Gemini that
you're using, the assistant.
질문을 하면
응답이 나오죠.
So you ask a question
and you have a response.
그리고 요약처럼
다른 작업들도 있습니다.
And then you have other tasks
as well, like summarization,
예를 들어, 기사를 요약하거나
you want to summarize
an article, let's say,
혹은 단순히 무언가를 생성하는 작업도 있습니다.
or just generate something.
예를 들어, 코드를 생성하거나 시를 생성하는 등
여러 가지 유형이 있을 수 있습니다.
So something can be generate
codes, generate a poem,
생성할 수 있는 것은 정말 다양합니다.
can also be a lot of things.
좋습니다.
Cool.
이제 각 작업 종류를 하나씩 살펴보면서
So now what we will do is go
through these tasks one by one
사람들이 보통 어떻게 접근하는지
예시를 들어 설명하겠습니다.
to just illustrate what
people typically handle with.
먼저 첫 번째 분류 작업부터
시작해보겠습니다.
So we're going to start
with the first bucket, which
이것이 분류 버킷입니다.
is the classification bucket.
여기서는 예시로
And here we're
going to illustrate
감정 추출 작업을 다뤄보겠습니다.
this with the sentiment
extraction task.
예를 들어, 어떤 문장이 있다고 해봅시다.
So let's suppose
we have a sentence,
"이 테디베어는 정말 귀엽다." 이런 문장입니다.
"this teddy bear is so cute."
우리 모델이 이 문장을 긍정적인 감정으로
예측하길 원합니다.
We want our model to predict
this to be a positive sentiment.
이때 주로 사용하는 것은 감정 추출 데이터셋입니다.
So typically what you
would use is sentiment
감정 추출 데이터셋을 활용하는 거죠.
extraction data sets.
아까 언급한 영화 리뷰 데이터는
IMDb 평가 데이터입니다.
So I mentioned movie reviews,
so this is IMDb critiques.
그리고 제품 리뷰 같은 것도 있고,
But you also have
reviews about products,
예를 들면 Amazon 리뷰나 트윗 같은 데이터도 있습니다.
so Amazon reviews or tweets.
이제는 Twitter가 X로 이름이 바뀌었으니, X 포스트도 여기에 포함됩니다.
Now I guess it's
called X, so X posts.
이런 출력 결과를 평가하는 방법은
And the way you would
evaluate such outputs
일반적으로 전통적인 분류 지표들을 사용하는 것입니다.
would be by typically using
traditional classification
여기서 사용하는 주요 지표들을 살펴보겠습니다.
metrics.
우선 정확도(accuracy)가 있는데,
So you have accuracy,
which is what
전체 관측값 중에서
is the percentage
of the observations
정확히 예측한 비율을 의미합니다.
that you correctly predicted.
그리고 중요한 지표 두 가지가 더 있습니다.
But you also have
two key metrics,
이 두 지표를 다시 한번 짚고 넘어가겠습니다.
which I'm just going to remind.
모두가 잘 알고 있는지 확신할 수는 없어서요.
I'm not sure if everyone
knows about them.
첫 번째는 정밀도(precision)인데,
So one is precision,
which is, out of all
모델이 긍정이라고 예측한 것들 중에서
the positive predictions
that you made,
실제로 맞은 비율입니다.
which ones were correct?
그리고 두 번째는 재현율(recall)입니다.
And then the second
one is recall.
실제 정답 레이블 전체 중에서
Out of all the true
labels, how many of them
정확히 긍정으로 예측한 비율이 재현율입니다.
did you correctly predict
as being positive?
여기서 F1 점수라는 지표도 사용하는데,
And you have this metric
called the F1 score, which
이것은 정밀도와 재현율의 조화평균(harmonic mean)을
basically takes the
harmonic mean of precision
하나의 수치로 나타내주는 지표입니다.
and recall to just
give you one number.
그렇다면 왜 이렇게 여러 지표들이 필요한지 궁금할 수 있습니다.
So now you may wonder, why do
you need all these metrics?
간단히 말해서,
So the short answer is that
sometimes you have tasks
클래스 불균형이 심한 데이터셋이나 과제가
and data sets where your
classes are very imbalanced.
종종 존재하기 때문입니다. 예를 들어,
So for instance, you can
have 99% of your data set
전체 데이터의 99%가 긍정 레이블이고,
that is a positive label,
and then only 1% of the data
나머지 1%만 부정인 경우도 있습니다.
set which is negative.
이럴 때 정확도 같은 지표만 사용하면
And so here if you take
a metric like accuracy,
굉장히 오해를 불러올 수 있습니다.
can be very misleading.
만약 모델이 모든 샘플을 다수 클래스 쪽으로만 예측하면
Because if you have a model
that would predict everything
정확도는 높게 나오겠지만, 그런 모델은
as the majority class, then you
will have a great classifier,
실제로 좋은 분류기는 아닙니다.
but that's not the case.
그래서 여기에서 정밀도와 재현율이 중요한 역할을 합니다.
So that's why precision and
recall really play a role.
지금까지가 첫 번째 범주에 관한 내용이었습니다.
So that's for the first one.
이제 두 번째 NLP 태스크 범주로 넘어가겠습니다.
So now let's move to the
second category of NLP tasks.
이번에는 다중 분류(multi-classification) 범주입니다.
So this one is the
multi-classification category.
여러분은 입력 텍스트를 받아서 여러 가지를 예측하게 됩니다.
So you have an input text and
you predict multiple things.
여기서는 NER 태스크를 예시로 설명할 텐데요,
And we're illustrating this
with the NER task, which
앞서 말했듯이 NER은
as I mentioned is
about identifying
주어진 단어의 범주를 식별하는 과제입니다.
the category of given words.
예를 들어, 여기에서는 곰인형이
And so here, for instance, we
want to identify a teddy bear
하나의 엔티티인지 식별하고 싶을 수 있습니다.
as being an entity.
이 경우에는 분류 평가 지표를 쓸 수 있습니다.
I guess for that, you would use
classification metrics, but not
하지만 문장 단위가 아니라 토큰 단위나
at the sentence level, but
more either at the token level
엔티티-타입 단위로 평가하게 됩니다.
or at the entity-type level.
여기서 말하는 엔티티-타입이란, 예를 들어
And by that I mean, let's
suppose you have a category,
'location' 같은 범주를 말합니다.
let's say location.
해당 범주에 속하는 단어를 우리가
And you want to know how
well you're predicting
얼마나 잘 예측하는지 알고 싶어진다는 거죠.
words in that category.
그래서 보통 이런 지표들은
So you would typically
aggregate these metrics
각 범주별로 집계해서 봅니다.
as a function of that.
좋습니다.
Cool.
이제 마지막 범주로 넘어가 보겠습니다.
OK, let's go to the
last category, which
제가 아까 언급한 것처럼, 이 범주가 가장 많이 쓰입니다.
is, as I mentioned,
the most popular one.
여기서는 텍스트를 입력받아서 텍스트를 출력합니다.
So this one is
text in, text out.
이 예시로 기계번역 태스크를 들 수 있습니다.
So I'm illustrating this
with the machine translation
기계번역은 소스 언어의 텍스트를
task, which is around
translating a text from a source
타깃 언어로 변환하는 과제입니다.
language to a target language.
예를 들어 영어에서 프랑스어로 번역하는 경우가 있습니다.
So here you have the example
with English to French.
'So cute teddy bear is reading'은 프랑스어로
'un ours en peluche mignon lit'가 됩니다.
So cute teddy bear is reading,
un ours en peluche mignon lit.
이런 경우에는 데이터셋을 구하기가 좀 더 어렵습니다.
So for that, I guess it's
harder to get data sets,
여기서는 텍스트 쌍이 필요하기 때문이죠.
because here you need
to have pairs of texts.
이렇게 아주 많이 쓰이는 데이터셋이 있습니다.
So you have a very
popular data set
WMT라고 부르는데,
Workshop on Machine Translation의 약자입니다.
that's called WMT, which
stands for Workshop on Machine
즉 기계 번역 워크숍이라는 뜻이죠.
Translation.
이 데이터셋에는 여러 언어쌍의 문장 쌍이 많이 포함되어 있습니다.
And that one contains a
bunch of paired sequences
다양한 언어로 구성되어 있죠.
in different languages.
예를 들어 영어-프랑스어, 영어-독일어 같은 쌍이 있습니다.
So for instance, you have the
English-French, English-German,
이 중에는 European Parliament 데이터셋에서 온 것도 있습니다.
coming from the European
Parliament data set,
예를 들면 그렇습니다.
for instance.
여기서 이런 번역 결과를 평가하려면,
So to evaluate
those, to evaluate
모델의 성능을 평가하는 일이 실제로는 훨씬 더 까다롭습니다.
the performance of your model,
it's actually a lot more tricky.
왜냐하면 한 문장을 번역하는 방법이 여러 가지가 있을 수 있기 때문입니다.
Because, as you can imagine,
you can have many different ways
하나의 문장을 여러 방식으로 번역할 수 있죠.
to translate something.
여기 있는 많은 분들이 두세 개 이상의 언어를 하실 수도 있을 텐데요,
I'm sure many of us in the
room are bilingual, trilingual.
바로 그 점이 번역 평가를 어렵게 만드는 이유입니다.
So that's what is
making it this hard.
그래서 과거에는 여러 가지 규칙 기반 평가 지표를 사용했습니다.
So in the past, people have
used several rule-based metrics
그렇게 평가를 했었죠.
to do that.
여러분도 BLEU라는 평가 지표를 들어보셨을 겁니다.
So one that you may
have heard is BLEU.
BLEU는 Bilingual Evaluation Under Study의 약자입니다.
BLEU stands for Bilingual
Evaluation Under Study.
이 지표는 자신의 번역이
And it is a measure of how
well your translation stands
기준(reference) 번역과 얼마나 유사한지를 측정합니다.
with respect to
a reference text.
ROUGE도 마찬가지인데, ROUGE는 사실 여러 지표 모음이고요,
Same story for ROUGE, which is
actually a suite of metrics,
BLEU와는 다른 방식으로 평가를 하게 됩니다.
but captures that
in a different way.
흥미롭게도 머신러닝 커뮤니티에서는
And you will see that the
machine learning community
BLEU라는 단어가 프랑스어로 '파랑'이라는 뜻이고,
is funny, because BLEU--
ROUGE는 '빨강'이라는 뜻이라는 걸 아시는지 모르겠습니다.
I'm not sure if you know
French-- means blue,
즉, ROUGE는 빨강이라는 뜻이죠.
but rouge means red.
이렇게 해서 재미를 주려고 한 것 같습니다.
So I guess they tried
to add some fun in this.
다만 이런 지표들의 문제는
But the problem
with these metrics
항상 기준(reference) 텍스트가 필요하다는 점입니다.
is that you always
need a reference text.
즉, 결국 레이블이 필요하다는 얘기죠.
So you basically need labels.
그리고 실제로는 라벨을 갖추는 것이 비용이 많이 듭니다.
And in practice, having
labels is very cost expensive.
라벨을 얻으려면 시간도 오래 걸리고,
많은 비용도 필요합니다.
It takes a lot of time, a
lot of money to get labels.
이후 강의에서 우리가
이 부분을 자세히 살펴볼 텐데요,
And we will see
later in the class
최근 LLM 분야에서의 발전 덕분에,
that with the progress that
we have made in the LLM space,
혹은 LLM 커뮤니티의 발전 덕분에,
or that the community has
made in the LLM space,
이런 참조 방식의 평가 지표를
이제는 굳이 쓰지 않아도 됩니다.
we can actually forego of
this reference-based metrics
대신 참조가 필요 없는 평가 방식으로
옮겨갈 수 있게 되었죠.
and go towards a more
reference-free metrics.
이 부분도 뒤에서 다시 다루겠습니다.
And we will see that later on.
그리고 마지막으로 사람들이 가끔 사용하는
지표가 있는데요,
And then the last metric that I
will say that people sometimes
그것이 바로 '퍼플렉서티'(perplexity)입니다.
use is called perplexity.
'퍼플렉서티'는 오직 모델이 출력한
확률 값만을 봅니다.
And perplexity only looks
at the probabilities
즉, 모델이 내놓은 확률값을 기반으로 계산합니다.
that are output by the model.
간단히 말해서, 모델이 현재 출력을 보고
얼마나 놀라는지를 수치로 나타냅니다.
And it basically
quantifies how surprised
즉, 모델이 자기 출력에 얼마나 놀라는지 측정하는 것이죠.
the model is by its output.
그래서 BLEU나 ROUGE는 점수가 높을수록 좋고,
So BLEU and ROUGE,
the higher the better.
퍼플렉서티는 점수가 낮을수록 더 좋습니다.
Perplexity, the
lower the better.
그리고 LLM이 본격적으로 주목받기 시작한 것은
2022년부터라고 할 수 있습니다.
And I guess LLMs have been
a hot topic since 2022.
하지만 실제로는 이 분야의 역사가
훨씬 전부터 시작됐습니다.
But actually, the field goes
way back, way before that year.
예를 들어 80년대에도,
곧 살펴보겠지만
So in the '80s, we'll
see it in a second,
이미 그 당시에도 한 부류의 모델들이
고안된 바 있습니다.
but there's a class of models
that were actually thought
즉, 80년대에도 이런 생각이 나왔다는 거죠.
of, even in the '80s.
또 90년대에는 LSTM이 등장했고,
이 부분도 곧 다룰 예정입니다.
And the '90s, we had LSTMs that
we'll see also in a second.
그런데 그 시기에는 문제가 있었습니다.
But the problem was,
during that time,
당시에는 인터넷이 없었고,
we didn't have the internet.
계산 자원도 매우 부족했습니다.
We didn't have a lot of compute.
이게 바로 오늘날의 모델이
학습되지 못했던 주요한 한계 중 하나였죠.
And I guess this was one of
the limiting factors which
그래서 당시에는 지금 같은 모델들이
학습될 수 없었습니다.
prevented the models from
today from being trained.
그 후 최근에는 여러 가지 중요한 발전이 있었습니다.
And then more recently,
we've had several advances.
특히 Word2vec은 의미 있는 임베딩을 계산하는 데
선구적인 연구 중 하나였습니다.
So Word2vec was really
one of the pioneering work
즉, 단어 간 의미를 담는 임베딩 자체를
구현한 초기 연구라 할 수 있겠습니다.
in just computing
meaningful embeddings.
이 내용은 곧 살펴보겠습니다.
And we'll see it in a second.
그리고 물론 이후에는 트랜스포머가 등장했고,
And then, of course, we
had the transformers,
이 트랜스포머는 2017년에 발표된 논문에서 제안됐습니다.
which were part of a paper that
was published in 2017, which
이 논문이 바로 현재 모든 모델의
기반이 되고 있습니다.
is basically at the foundation
of all of the models
여러분이 오늘날 볼 수 있는 모든 모델들이죠.
that you see today.
그리고 이 모델들은 단순히 계산 자원뿐 아니라,
And then these models, they just
were scaled up, both by compute,
학습에 사용된 데이터의 규모까지
크게 확장되었습니다.
but also in terms of the data
that was used to train them.
이렇게 해서 LLM이라는 명칭이 나왔습니다.
And that's how LLMs were dubbed.
이러한 흐름은 2020년대에 들어서 본격화됐다고 볼 수 있습니다.
And I guess these are
more like the 2020s.
이 부분도 곧 다루겠습니다.
But yeah, I guess
we'll see those.
좋습니다.
Cool.
여기까지 전체적인 내용에 대해 질문 있나요?
Any questions on, I
guess, the high level?
다들 괜찮으신가요?
Everyone good?
좋습니다.
Cool.
자, 그럼 첫 번째로,
So I guess the first
question that I
우리가 스스로에게 던져야 할 질문이 무엇일까요?
want to ask ourselves
is, what we want to do
우리는 텍스트를 다룰 수 있는 모델을 만들고 싶습니다.
is to have a model
that handles text.
하지만 모델은 숫자를 이해하지,
텍스트를 직접 이해하지는 못합니다.
But models, they
understand numbers,
즉, 모델은 원래 텍스트 자체를
이해하지 못하는 것이죠.
they don't really
understand text.
그래서 텍스트를 어떻게든 처리해서
So we need to somehow do
something with that text
좀 더 정량적으로,
to make it more
quantifiable, something
모델이 이해할 수 있는 형태로 만들어줘야 합니다.
that a model can understand.
예를 들어, 한 문장을 본다면,
So if you look at a
sentence, for instance,
"a cute teddy bear is reading"이라는 문장이 있다고 할 때,
"a cute teddy bear is reading,"
you first need to ask yourself,
이 문장을 어떻게 잘라서 모델에 넣을 수 있을지
생각해봐야 합니다.
how can you cut this sentence
to pass it to a model?
이 과정을 토큰화(tokenization)라고 합니다.
So this part is
called tokenization.
토큰화는 기본적으로
And what that
entails is basically
텍스트를 어떤 임의의 단위로 잘라내는 것을 의미합니다.
cutting the text with respect
to some arbitrary unit of text.
이를 구현하는 방법에는 여러 가지가 있습니다.
So there are several
ways of doing this.
먼저 완전히 임의적으로 나누는 방식을 생각해볼 수 있습니다.
I guess the first way is doing
it completely arbitrarily.
예를 들어, 여기서는 "a."가
So here, for instance,
you would have "a."
하나의 텍스트 단위가 됩니다.
That would be one unit of text.
"Cute"도 또 다른 텍스트 단위가 될 수 있죠.
"Cute" could be
another unit of text.
"Teddy bear" 역시 또 다른 단위가 되고, 이런 식으로 나눌 수 있습니다.
"Teddy bear" would be
another one, and so on.
그리고 참고로, 이러한 텍스트의 단위를
And by the way,
the unit of text is
토큰(token)이라고 부르기 때문에, 이 방식을 토큰화(tokenization)라고 합니다.
called a token, which is why the
method is called tokenization.
또 다른 방법으로는, 단어 단위로 나누는 방법도 있습니다.
Another way would be to
just separate by words.
하지만 항상 장단점이 존재하겠죠.
But I guess we would have
always pros and cons.
우리가 달성하려는 목표 중 하나는
I guess one of the goals
that we want to achieve
이렇게 나눈 토큰들을 의미 있게 표현하는 것입니다.
is for us to then be able
to represent these tokens
즉, 의미 있는 방식으로 표현해야 하죠.
in a meaningful way.
그런데 단어 단위로 나누면 생기는 단점이 있습니다.
So one con with doing
this at the word level
겉보기엔 비슷한 단어들도
is you will end up with
words that look similar,
사실 서로 다른 토큰으로 처리된다는 점입니다.
but that are actually
considered as different tokens.
여기서의 한계는,
And I guess the
limitation here is
이렇게 비슷하지만 다른 토큰 각각에 대해 임베딩을
you will need to
compute embeddings
따로 계산해야 한다는 점이죠.
for these similar
yet different tokens
그리고 이런 임베딩이 비슷하도록 만들어주는 것도 필요합니다.
and somehow make their
embeddings similar.
예시를 들어보겠습니다.
So I'll give you an example.
예를 들어, "bear"라는 단어가 있다고 해보죠.
So let's suppose I
have the word "bear."
그리고 그 복수형인 "bears"라는 단어도 있습니다.
And then you have another
word, plural form "bears."
이 두 단어는 서로 매우 비슷하죠.
So these two words,
they are very similar.
하나는 단수, 다른 하나는 복수형일 뿐입니다.
Just one is singular,
the other one is plural.
이렇게 단어 단위로 토큰화를 하면
If we go ahead with the
word-level tokenization,
결국 완전히 별개의 두 개 엔티티가 생깁니다.
then we will end up with
just two different entities,
그리고 이 둘은 그냥 다르게 인식됩니다.
which are basically just
considered as different.
"run"과 "runs"처럼 동사의 다양한 형태도 마찬가지입니다.
Same with "run," and then
"runs," variations of verbs.
바로 이런 이유로,
So for that reason,
people have dug
사람들은 토크나이저의 한 분류인
into a category
of tokenizers that
서브워드(subword) 토크나이저에 주목하게 되었고,
이는 어근을 잘 활용하기 위함입니다.
are called subword tokenizers,
which is around leveraging roots
단어의 공통된 어근을 찾기 위해서입니다.
of words in order to find what
are the common roots that we
이 단어들에서 찾을 수 있는 공통 어근이 무엇인지 보는 거죠.
can find in these words.
예를 들어, "bear"와 "bears"처럼요.
So, for instance,
for bear and bears,
"bear"라는 어근이 두 단어에 모두 들어가게 됩니다.
you would have the bear
particle that would be shared.
이 방식의 장점은 단어의 어근을 활용할 수 있다는 점입니다.
And so I guess the pro is
that you get to leverage
즉, 단어의 어근을 공통적으로 쓸 수 있죠.
the root of the words.
반면 단점은 시퀀스가 더 길어진다는 겁니다.
But then the con here is that
your sequence would be longer.
이게 왜 단점이 되는지는 곧 살펴보겠습니다.
And we will see
why this is a con.
나중에 자세히 설명할 텐데, 미리 간단히 말씀드리면,
I guess later on, I guess
I can give you a preview.
이러한 모델들의 연산 복잡도는
So the complexity
of these models
시퀀스 길이에 따라 결정됩니다.
is also a function of
the sequence length.
즉, 처리해야 할 토큰이 많아질수록
So the more tokens
you have to process,
모델을 실행하는 데 더 많은 시간이 걸립니다.
the more time it will take
for your model to run,
모델이 모든 토큰을 전부 처리해야 하기 때문이죠.
because it needs to basically
process all these tokens.
이런 점이 단점입니다.
So that's one con.
장점은 단어의 어근을 활용할 수 있다는 것이고,
So pro is it leverages
the root of words.
단점은 시퀀스가 길어진다는 겁니다.
Con is it just makes
your sequences longer.
마지막으로 또 다른 토큰화 방법 카테고리가 있습니다.
You have a last category of
ways of tokenizing things, which
바로 문자 단위로 토큰화하는 방식입니다.
is just going at
the character level,
각 문자를 하나씩 분리해서 토큰화하는 방식이죠.
just like taking out characters.
여러분이나 저나 메시지를 쓸 때를 생각해 보면,
So here, I guess, you and
I when we write a message,
가끔씩 철자를 틀리기도 합니다.
we typically have
sometimes misspellings.
서브워드 방식으로 토큰화할 경우에는
And with the subword way
of tokenizing things,
이렇게 철자가 틀린 단어를 인식하지 못할 수도 있습니다.
you may not be able to
recognize the word that
철자가 틀린 단어인 경우에 그렇죠.
has been misspelled.
하지만 문자 단위 토크나이저라면,
And this is something that
the character-level tokenizer
이런 부분까지도 더 잘 다룰 수 있습니다.
can, I guess, take
into consideration.
하지만 여기서의 문제는 시퀀스 길이가
But here the problem is you
have a sequence length that's
훨씬 더 길어지기 때문에 모델이
much, much longer, which
will make your model,
해당 시퀀스를 처리하는 데 시간이 훨씬 더 오래 걸린다는 점입니다.
I guess, take much more time
to process the sequence.
그래서 이게 첫 번째 단점입니다.
So that's one con.
그리고 또 다른 단점은,
And then the other
con is, I guess,
각 토큰을 표현하려고 할 때,
when you want to represent
each of these tokens,
이 토큰이 어떤 의미인지
알아내기가 매우 어렵다는 점입니다.
I guess it's very hard to
know that a representation
특히 글자 하나의 임베딩이
무엇을 의미하는지 모르겠죠.
of a letter really means.
예를 들면, 알파벳 U라는 글자의
임베딩이 실제로 무엇을 의미하는지
Like, what does the
representation of the letter U
알아내기가 매우 어렵습니다.
mean.
진짜 쉽지 않은 문제입니다.
It's very hard.
네, 좋습니다.
OK, cool.
여기까지 간단히 정리하겠습니다.
So I have just a quick recap.
워드 레벨 토크나이징은
매우 직관적이고 단순하게,
So word-level is a super naive
way, super simple way of,
텍스트를 임의 단위로
나누는 방식입니다.
I guess, dividing your
text into arbitrary units.
하지만 문제는 앞에서 이야기했듯이,
But then the problem
is, as we mentioned,
단어의 어근을 활용하지 못한다는 점입니다.
we do not leverage
the root of words.
그리고 언급하진 않았지만
여기에 용어가 하나 있습니다.
And I did not mention
this, but there is a term.
무언가를 잘라서,
추론할 때
Whenever you cut something
and then at inference time
예측을 하려고 하면,
when you want to
make a prediction,
반드시 필요한 전제조건이 하나 있습니다.
I guess, one prerequisite
that you have is
학습할 때 봤던 토큰을
추론할 때도 가지고 있어야 한다는 겁니다.
that you need to have the token
that you saw at training time,
즉, 학습셋에 반드시 포함돼 있어야 합니다.
you need to have it
in your training sets.
문제는 만약 추론할 때
And the problem is, let's
suppose at inference time
텍스트를 단어 단위로 잘라서,
you cut your text into words.
학습 시에 보지 못한 단어가 나온다면,
And let's suppose you have not
seen a word at training time.
그 단어를 미지(unknown)로 표시해야 합니다.
You will need to
mark it as unknown.
이런 경우를 OOV, 즉 Out Of Vocabulary라고 부릅니다.
And so this thing is called
OOV, Out Of Vocabulary.
다행히도, 서브워드 레벨 토크나이저는
So luckily, the
subword-level tokenizer
이 문제를 어느 정도 완화해줍니다.
mitigates that problem.
그래서 OOV 위험이 낮아지지만
아예 없어지지는 않습니다.
So you have a lower risk of
OOV, but still you can have.
또 장점으로는,
And as we mentioned,
in terms of the pro,
단어의 어근을 활용할 수 있다는 점이 있습니다.
you leverage the
roots of the words.
그리고 문자 단위 토크나이저는 오타나
And then character-level, it's
robust to our misspellings
대소문자 오류에도 강인합니다.
and our casing errors.
하지만 이렇게 하면 연산 속도가
굉장히 느려진다는 단점이 있습니다.
But the problem is it makes
computations just much slower.
그리고 시퀀스의 길이도 매우 길어지게 됩니다.
And your sequences would
be very, very long,
이렇게 되면 추론 시간도
which will also
make your, I guess,
훨씬 더 길어질 수밖에 없습니다.
inference time much higher.
여기까지 괜찮으신가요?
That sound good?
이 부분이 바로 텍스트를 다룰 때의
기본적인 원리라고 할 수 있습니다.
I guess this is really
the foundation, I guess,
텍스트를 어떻게 처리할지에 관한 내용이죠.
how to handle things with text.
전체적으로 이해가 되셨나요?
But yeah, does that
make sense overall?
좋습니다.
Cool.
자, 이제 우리가 한 일은
입력 텍스트를 받아서
OK, so now what we did
is we took an input text.
기본적으로 그걸 토큰 단위로
조각낸 것입니다.
What we did is we cut it into
parts that are basically tokens.
이제 모델이 이 토큰들을 이해하려면,
So in order for our model
to understand these tokens,
각 토큰마다 표현 방식을 찾아줘야 합니다.
we need to find a
representation for each of them.
그래서 이제 이 부분을 같이 살펴보겠습니다.
So here, we're going
to take a look at this.
이걸 단어 표현(word representation)이라고 부르기도 하는데,
So that's called a
word representation.
좀 더 정확히 말하면
Or I guess, in a
more correct way,
토큰 표현(token representation)이라고 할 수 있습니다.
it should be token
representation.
즉, 각각의 토큰을 어떻게 표현할지 방법을 찾는 것이죠.
So we want to find a way to
represent each of these tokens.
간단하고 직관적인 방법으로는
So the simple and
naive way to do this
각 단어마다, 혹은 각 토큰마다
원-핫 벡터를 할당하는 방식이 있습니다.
would be to just assign the
one hot vector for each word
각 토큰마다 원-핫 벡터를 할당하는 거죠.
or for each token.
예를 들어,
So for instance,
let's suppose we have
세 개의 토큰으로 이루어진 어휘집이 있다고 해봅시다.
a vocabulary of three tokens--
book, soft, teddy bear가 있다고 하면,
book, soft, and teddy bears.
예를 들어 soft는
We would have, let's say, soft.
1, 0, 0 벡터가 될 것입니다.
That is 1, 0, 0 vector.
teddy bear는 0, 1, 0 벡터가 되고,
Teddy bear, that is, let's
say a 0, 1, 0 vector.
book은 0, 0, 1 벡터가 됩니다.
And book, that is, let's
say, a 0, 0, 1 vector.
이걸 원-핫 인코딩, 약자로 OHE라고 부릅니다.
So this is called a
One-Hot Encoding, OHE.
이 방식은 보통 자주 등장합니다.
We'll typically see.
꽤 흥미롭죠.
So cool.
이렇게 해서 토큰을 표현할 수 있습니다.
This is a way to
represent our tokens.
하지만 사람들이 실제로 원하는 것은,
But basically what
people want to do
이 토큰들을 비교해서
is compare these
tokens to basically see
어떤 토큰끼리 더 비슷한지를 알아내는 겁니다.
which ones are more
similar to what other ones.
그래서 자주 사용하는 유사도 측정 방식이
So common similarity
measure that people use
코사인 유사도라는 것입니다.
is something called
cosine similarity.
아마 들어본 적 있을 수도 있겠네요.
I'm not sure if you
have heard of it.
간단히 생각하면,
So you can think of
it as just seeing
이 벡터들이 n차원 공간에서 어떤 각도를 이루고 있는지 보는 겁니다.
what angle these vectors make
in the n dimensional space.
만약 같은 방향을 가리키고 있다면,
And if, I guess, they are
pointing in the same direction,
둘이 비슷하다고 볼 수 있겠죠.
then maybe they're similar.
반대로 직교한다면, 서로 독립적이라고 볼 수 있습니다.
Maybe if they're orthogonal,
maybe they're independent.
그리고 완전히 반대 방향이면,
And if they're
completely opposite, then
둘이 반대라고 할 수 있겠죠.
maybe they're opposite.
이게 우리가 가지고 가야 할 기본적인 마인드셋입니다.
That's basically the mental
model we want to go into.
그런데 문제는, 만약 여러분이 토큰을 원-핫 방식으로 표현하면
So the problem is, if you
represent your tokens in a one
결국 모든 벡터가 서로 직교하게 된다는 겁니다.
hot fashion, you will end
up with all your vectors
모든 벡터가 서로 직교하게 되죠.
being orthogonal to one another.
이게 바로 문제입니다.
So that's the problem.
그래서 우리가 이상적으로 원하는 것은,
So ideally, what we
want is for tokens
의미가 같거나 비슷한 토큰들은
that mean the same or
similar to basically have
유사도가 높아지는 것입니다.
a high similarity.
그리고 비슷하지 않은, 관련 없는 토큰들은
And for tokens that are
not similar on about
서로 더 직교하게 되는 것이죠.
different thing, to
be more orthogonal.
예시로, 곰인형은 부드럽다고 할 수 있습니다.
So here, just for illustrative
purposes, teddy bears are soft.
그래서 곰인형과 부드럽다는 토큰은
So you want teddy bear
and soft to be, I guess,
유사도가 높게 나오기를 바랍니다.
with a high similarity.
예를 들어, 테디베어와 책처럼 서로 독립적인 경우에는
And let's say teddy bear and
book, which is independent,
이 둘 사이의 유사도가 0에 가깝기를 바랍니다.
you want them to be closer to 0.
이게 바로 우리가 원하는 것입니다.
So that's what you want.
이게 바로 원-핫 인코딩에서 얻는 특성이고,
That's what you have
with one-hot encoding,
우리가 바라는 모습이기도 합니다.
and that's what you want.
네, 그렇습니다.
Yeah.
네?
Sorry?
아, 알겠습니다.
Oh, I see.
질문은, 왜 노름(norm)이 중요한가요?
The question is, why do
you care about the norm?
코사인 유사도는 사실 벡터의 노름으로 정규화된 값입니다.
So I guess cosine similarity is
actually normalized by norms.
즉, 내적(dot product)을 사용합니다.
So it's dot products.
아, 제가 왜 여기서 내적만 썼냐고 물으신 건가요?
Oh, you mean why did I just put
dot product here instead of 2?
아, 이해했습니다.
Oh, I see.
질문은, 왜 우리는 노름(norm)에 신경 쓰지 않는가입니다.
And your question is, why do
we not care about the norm?
좋아요, 아마 시청자분들도 질문을 이해하셨을 겁니다.
Cool, I guess the viewers
know the question.
이런 척도들은 모두 유사성을 측정하려는 방식입니다.
I guess these measures,
they are all measures.
이런 방식으로 유사성을 잡아내려고 여러 방법을 쓰는 것이죠.
They are all ways to try to
capture these similarity things.
그래서 노름에 신경 쓰지 않는 이유가 궁금할 수 있는데요,
So I guess why do you
not care about the norm?
사람들이 이런 방식으로 수치를 정해온 결과라고 할 수 있습니다.
I guess it's how people
have tried to quantify that.
자신의 벡터가 어떻게 학습됐는지 보면서,
I guess you will need to see
how your vectors are trained
노름이 특별한 의미를 가지는지도 확인할 필요가 있습니다.
and whether the norm would
be indicative of something.
제가 드릴 수 있는 가장 좋은 답은, 이것도 하나의 척도라는 점입니다.
I guess the best answer I
can give you is, I guess,
이건 하나의 측정 방식입니다.
this is a measure.
완벽한 기준은 아니에요.
This is not the perfect measure.
사람들은 내적도 척도로 사용하기도 합니다.
People may use also dot
product as a measure,
하지만 좀 더 좋은 답을 드리긴 어렵네요.
but yeah, I don't have
a great answer for you.
그래도 우리가 보통 관심 가지는 것은
But as long as you
capture, I guess,
벡터들이 어떤 방향을 가리키는지이고,
how these vectors
they're pointing,
보통은 벡터 사이의 각도가 더 중요합니다.
I guess, typically what you care
about is the angle between them.
하지만 일반적으로는
But typically, you
don't really take
보통은 벡터의 노름까지는 신경 쓰지 않습니다.
into consideration the norm.
좋습니다. 질문 있으신가요?
Cool, any questions?
다른 질문 있으신가요?
Any other questions?
네, 질문해 주세요.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
좋은 질문입니다.
It's a great question.
질문은 어휘집 크기에 관한 내용입니다.
So the question is
around size of vocabulary
그리고 이것이 단어, 서브워드 선택에 어떻게 영향을 주는지에 대한 것이네요.
and how that would inform
the choice with respect
또 언어마다 어떻게 달라지는지도 포함되어 있습니다.
to word, subword, and how
that changes across languages.
아주 좋은 질문입니다.
So great question.
정확히 말하면, 이건 정말로 여러분이 해결하려는 태스크에 따라 다릅니다.
So I would say it
really depends, first
만약 한 언어에서만 처리하는 태스크라면
of all, on the tasks that
you're trying to achieve.
그 언어만 사용하면 됩니다.
If your task is just
about one language,
보통은 그 언어만을 다루게 됩니다.
you will just take
that same language.
여기서 언급한 여러 이유 때문에 보통 서브워드 토크나이저를 사용합니다.
You would typically go with a
subword tokenizer just because
방금 말씀드렸던 이유들 때문입니다.
of the reasons that
we mentioned here.
서브워드는 단어의 어근을 식별할 수 있게 해주면서,
So I guess subwords is a
nice trade-off between being
동시에 OOV 위험도 줄여주는 좋은 절충안입니다.
able to identify
words by their roots,
이렇게 어근 정보를 활용하면서도 OOV(Out-of-Vocabulary) 위험을 낮추는 효과가 있습니다.
like leveraging that, but also
running less into the OOV risk.
어휘집 크기 측면에서는, 실제로 여러 가지 시도가 있었습니다.
So in terms of the
size, I know that people
사람들이 다양한 실험을 해봤죠.
have tried different things.
영어의 경우에는 보통
I think typically
for English, you
어휘집 크기를 수만 단위로 맞추는 경우가 많습니다.
would target something on the
order of tens of thousands
대략 수만 개 정도의 어휘집을 목표로 합니다.
of vocabulary size.
하지만 요즘 모델들은 다국어와 코드까지 지원하죠.
But nowadays, the models,
they are multilingual,
소스 코드까지도 다룹니다.
they are also about codes.
그래서 최근에는 어휘집 크기가
So you will see that
the vocabulary size now
수십만 개에 이르는 경우도 있습니다.
is sometimes on the order
of hundreds of thousands.
중국어의 경우에는 또 차이가 있습니다.
So with respect to
Chinese, so I guess
중국어는 사용하는 글자가 다르기 때문이죠.
you have this difference in
characters that you're using.
라틴 계열은 알파벳을 사용하는 반면,
So for Latin, I guess
it's the alphabet
우리 모두 익숙한 알파벳입니다.
we're all accustomed to.
하지만 다른 언어의 경우에는,
But of course for
the other ones,
비슷한 개념이 있지만,
you'd have something
similar, but in I
그 언어의 문자 체계로 사용합니다.
guess the target
language character.
그래서 보통 한 언어는
수만 개 단위의 어휘 집 크기를 가집니다.
So yeah, I would say order of
magnitude, tens of thousands
여러 언어를 지원하면
수십만 개까지 커질 수도 있습니다.
for one language, hundreds of
thousands if it's multilingual.
이 정도 규모의 어휘 집을
목표로 삼는 것이 일반적입니다.
These are the order of magnitude
that you want to target for.
네, 좋습니다.
Cool, yeah.
좋은 질문이었습니다.
Great question.
자, 질문은 임베딩을 어떻게 구하느냐는 겁니다.
So the question is, how do
you get those embeddings?
사실 다음 슬라이드에서 다룰 내용입니다.
So it's actually the next slide.
그래서 이 부분을 지금 설명하겠습니다.
So I'm going to talk about this.
네, 좋습니다.
Cool, great.
이제 우리는 원-핫 인코딩이
토큰을 표현하는 좋은 방법이 아니라는 것을 알게 됐습니다.
So now that we know that
the one-hot encoding is not
그래서 우리가 하고 싶은 것은
이 임베딩을 데이터로부터 학습하는 것입니다.
a good way to represent
tokens, what we want to do
그리고 2010년대에 나왔던
논문을 언급했었는데요.
is to learn those
embeddings from the data.
아마 2013년에 나온 Word2vec이라는 논문이었습니다.
So I mentioned that there
was this paper that came out
이 논문이 인기를 끌었던 이유는,
in the 2010s-- so I think it was
2013-- that was called Word2vec.
임베딩을 직관적이고 해석 가능하게
보여줬기 때문입니다.
And the reason why
it was so popular
"king은 queen과 같다"처럼 이런 관계들을,
is because they showed a very
intuitive and interpretable way
"Paris는 France와 같다"를 "Berlin은 Germany와 같다"로 볼 수 있는 방식을 보여줬습니다.
of seeing these embeddings,
because they were saying
즉, 임베딩을 해석할 수 있는 방식이 도입된 것입니다.
something like, OK, king is to
queen, what this is to that,
이제 궁금한 것은, 이런 임베딩을 어떻게 만들었냐는 점입니다.
like Paris is to France
what Berlin is to Germany.
그 논문에서는 임베딩을 계산하는 두 가지 방법을 제안했습니다.
So there was basically a way to
make sense of the embeddings.
첫 번째는 연속 단어 집합(Continuous Bag of Words)이고,
So now the question is,
how did they do that?
다른 하나는 스킵그램(Skip-gram)입니다.
So they had two ways of
computing these embeddings.
하지만 이 두 가지 방법 모두
So one way was called
continuous bag of words.
기본적으로 동일한 아이디어를 가지고 있습니다.
The other one was
called skip gram.
즉, 우리가 가진 텍스트 데이터를 활용해서
But they all rely
on the same idea,
그 안에 포함된 어떤 내용을 예측해보는 방식입니다.
which is let's just leverage
texts that we have, and then try
텍스트의 일부를 예측하는 것이 목표입니다.
to predict something
that is part of the text,
예를 들어, 문맥을 바탕으로 예측하는 방식이죠.
based on, let's
say, the context.
예를 들어, Continuous Bag of Words에서는
So for instance, continuous
bag of words, the goal
주변 단어들을 고려해서
is you take into consideration
the words that are
특정 타깃 단어 주변의 단어들을 보는 겁니다.
around a given target words.
그리고 목표는 그 타깃 단어를 예측하는 것입니다.
And your goal is to
predict that target word.
Skip gram은 이와 반대입니다.
And skip gram is the opposite.
타깃 단어에서 시작해서
You go from a
target word and you
그 주변의 단어들을 예측하려고 합니다.
want to predict the
words that are around it.
이런 식의 과제를 흔히 프록시 태스크라고 부릅니다.
So I guess this task is
commonly called a proxy task.
왜냐하면 결국 이 연습에서
Because at the end of the
day, in this exercise,
진짜로 중요한 건
what we care about
is not necessarily
반드시 다음 단어 예측이 아니기 때문입니다. 최소한 지금 단계에서는 말이죠.
to predict the next word,
or at least not yet.
우리가 원하는 것은 이러한 단어들의 의미 있는 표현을 학습하는 것입니다.
Our goal is to learn a
representation of these words
즉, 의미를 담고 있는 표현을 얻는 거죠.
that are meaningful.
여기서 핵심 아이디어는, 만약 모델이
And so here the idea is, if you
have a model that somehow knows
예를 들어 다음 단어를 예측할 수 있을 정도가 된다면,
how to predict, let's say,
the next word, then it
그 모델이 언어에 대해 어느 정도 이해를 갖추었다는 것을 의미합니다.
means that your model has some
understanding of how language
결국 이게 우리가 원하는 바죠.
works, which is
basically what you want.
우리는 언어의 특성을 반영하는 임베딩을 얻고 싶은 겁니다.
You basically want an
embedding that is reflective
예를 들면, king과 queen 같은 관계라든지,
of, I guess, what language
is, which is king and queen,
Paris와 France처럼 수도와 국가 관계 등,
or similar, Paris and
France, this is a capital.
이런 연관성이 임베딩에 담기길 원하죠.
You want to have these
associations embedded
이런 의미들이 표현 안에 잘 녹아들게 하는 것입니다.
in the representation.
이제 아주 간단한 예제를 하나 살펴보겠습니다.
And let's go through
a very simple example
이런 방식이 실제로 어떻게 작동하는지 예를 들어보죠.
of what that looks like.
여기에서 프록시 태스크가 다음 단어 예측이라고 가정해봅시다.
So here in our example, let's
suppose that our proxy task is
즉, 다음에 올 단어를 예측하는 겁니다.
about predicting the next word.
여기서는 아주 단순한 신경망 모델을 사용합니다.
So here what we take is
a very vanilla neural
이 모델은 크기가 v인 벡터를 입력받고,
network model, which basically
receives a vector of size v,
곱셈 연산과,
또 편향 항이 들어갑니다.
has multiplication
and a bias term
이를 통해 은닉 상태를 만들고,
여기서 다시 한 번 곱셈 연산을 해줍니다.
to get a hidden state, and then
another set of multiplications
이렇게 해서 최종 벡터를 얻습니다.
to get our final vector.
즉 여기서는 아주 단순한 신경망을 사용하고 있습니다.
So here it's basically a
very simple neural network.
입력은 크기가 v이고,
은닉 레이어는
So the input is of size v.
The hidden layer is of size
보통 어휘집 크기보다 훨씬 작은 d 차원을 가집니다.
d, which is typically much
smaller than the vocabulary.
어휘집의 크기는 보통
수만에서 수십만 단위가 됩니다.
So vocabulary is typically
like tens of thousands
혹은 수십만까지도 갈 수 있습니다.
or hundreds of thousands.
그래서 d 값은 보통 100 정도입니다.
So d is typically hundred.
예를 들어 768도 하나의 예시가 될 수 있죠.
Like, 768, for instance, is
one example of dimension.
즉 어휘집보다 훨씬 작은 수치입니다.
So it's much, much smaller.
여기서 우리가 하려는 것은
이런 프록시 태스크를 통해 단어 임베딩을 학습하는 것입니다.
So what we're trying to do is
to learn the word representation
즉, 이 프록시 태스크를 활용하는 거죠.
through this proxy task.
이제 우리가 할 일은,
And what we're
going to do is try
단어들을 입력으로 넣고, 다음 단어를 예측하는 방식입니다.
to consider the words as inputs
and predict the next word.
그럼 시퀀스의 첫 번째 단어로 시작해봅시다.
So let's go with the first
word of the sequence.
참고로 저는 토큰과 단어를 혼용해서 사용합니다.
So by the way, I use token
and words interchangeably.
예를 들어 우리가 "a"라는 단어를 가지고 있고,
다음 단어를 예측하고 싶다고 가정해봅시다.
So let's suppose we have the
word "a," and we want to predict
다음 단어는 "cute"라는 단어가 되겠죠.
the next word, which
is the word "cute."
즉 "a"라는 단어를,
원-핫 인코딩으로 변환한 다음
So what we do is we take the
word "a," we take the one-hot
이 표현을 신경망에 입력합니다.
encoding representation, and
we pass it through the network.
신경망에 익숙하다면 아시겠지만,
So here, if you're familiar
with neural networks,
여기서는 행렬과 벡터의 곱셈이 이루어집니다.
so here you have, I
guess, a multiplication
즉, 행렬과 이 벡터 사이의 곱셈이죠.
between a matrix
and this vector.
그리고 은닉 상태 표현이 만들어집니다.
So you have a hidden
state representation,
이것은 d 차원의 벡터가 됩니다.
which is a vector of size d.
예를 들어 d가 2라면, 값이 0.2와 0.9가 될 수 있습니다.
So here, let's suppose it's
0.2 and 0.9, so D equal 2.
그 다음 단계로 또 한 번 변환이 진행됩니다.
And then you have, I
guess, another pass here.
그리고 소프트맥스 함수를 거치면,
And then you get,
after softmax, a set
각각의 단어에 대한 확률값이 나오게 됩니다.
of probabilities
which are around
이렇게 해서 다음 단어가 무엇인지 예측하게 됩니다.
seeing what is the next word.
이 예시에서는 어휘집 크기가 6이라고 가정해봅시다.
So in this example, we have
a vocabulary of size 6.
먼저 첫 번째 단어가 일정 확률로 예측됩니다.
So the first word is
predicted with probability
첫 번째 단어는 0.2, 두 번째 단어는 0.4의 확률로 예측되고,
나머지 단어들도 각각 확률이 정해집니다.
0.2, second word, 0.4,
and then the other words
여기서는 나머지 단어들의 확률이 모두 0.1입니다.
are all 0.1 in this example.
이제 우리가 원하는 것은,
두 번째 단어가 예측되도록 만드는 것입니다.
So let's suppose that
we want to somehow
즉, 예측 확률을 최대화하려고 하는 거죠.
be able to maximize
our prediction
어휘집의 두 번째 단어, 즉 확률 0.4가 되는 경우를 최대한 맞추고 싶다고 하면,
to be the second word of the
vocabulary, which is the 0.4.
예측 결과를, 예를 들어,
So we basically compare the
prediction with, I guess,
0, 1, 0, 0, 0과 같은 형태,
즉 one-hot 인코딩 표현과 비교하는 겁니다.
0, 1, 0, 0, 0, which
is the representation
이게 바로 어휘집에서 두 번째 단어를 나타냅니다.
of the second word
of the vocabulary.
그리고 나서 역전파를 통해 가중치를 업데이트합니다.
And then we do the back
prop, we update the weights.
이 부분에 익숙하지 않은 분들도 계실 것 같습니다.
I'm not sure if everyone
is familiar with that part.
핵심은, 예측값이 나오면
But the idea here is, once
you obtain a prediction,
손실 값을 계산하고, 보통은 크로스 엔트로피를 사용합니다.
you compute the loss, so
typically cross-entropy,
이 손실 값이 실제 정답과 얼마나 차이가 나는지 알려줍니다.
which will determine how far off
you are from the true answer.
그 차이를 기반으로,
And based on that
difference, you're
가중치를 업데이트해서
going to update the
weights in order
예측 결과가 실제 답에 더 가까워지도록 만듭니다.
to make your prediction
closer to the truth.
바로 이런 과정을 거치는 거죠.
So that's what you do.
그리고 이 과정을 반복합니다.
And then you repeat
that process.
예를 들어 "cute"라는 단어를 생각해봅시다.
아까 말씀드렸듯이 어휘집의 두 번째 단어입니다.
Let's suppose you take the
word "cute," which, as we said,
즉, 어휘집의 두 번째 단어가 맞는 거죠.
is the second word
in the vocabulary.
one-hot 인코딩 표현은 0, 1, 0, 0, 0이 됩니다.
So the one-hot encoding
representation is 0, 1, 0, 0, 0.
이 네트워크를 통과시키면 은닉 상태를 얻게 되고,
So you go through that network,
you have a hidden state,
이때 벡터 값이 0.8, 0.4처럼 나올 수 있습니다.
like the vector is 0.8 and 0.4.
이 과정을 다시 반복하죠.
You do that again.
이런 식으로 다음 토큰을 예측하는 것이 목표입니다.
And what you want to do is
to predict the next token,
여기서는 다음 단어가 teddy bear로 주어졌다고 가정해봅시다.
and here is teddy bear.
이 예제에서 여러분의 모델은
다음 단어를 예측하게 됩니다.
And so you see now your
model in this example
이 예시에서 모델은 다음 단어를 'uniform'으로 예측하고 있습니다.
is predicting the next
word to be uniform,
하지만 우리는 'teddy bear'가 나올 확률이 더 높아지도록 만들고 싶죠.
but you want to somehow maximize
the probability for teddy bear.
이런 식으로 모든 단어에 대해 반복적으로 학습을 진행합니다.
So you go about doing this again
and again for all the words.
결국에는, 이런 과정을 통해 모델을 얻게 됩니다.
And at the end of the
day, you obtain a model
이 모델은 다음 단어를 예측하는 방법을 학습한 것이죠.
that learns how to predict the
next word, which is basically
이게 바로 우리가 사용하는 대리 과제입니다.
the proxy task.
이제 우리가 할 일은, 모델이 학습한 표현을 활용하는 것입니다.
And what you're going to do
is to take the representation
여기서 말하는 표현은, 초록색 유닛으로 표시된 그 부분입니다.
that the model learns,
which is the green units.
이제는 단어마다 이렇게 표현이 만들어집니다.
So what happens now is
every time you have a word,
각 단어를 원-핫 인코딩으로 표현하면 됩니다.
you just represent that as a
one-hot encoding representation.
이 원-핫 벡터에 가중치를 곱해주면
And you just multiply
this with these weights,
초록색으로 나타난 표현이 만들어집니다.
and then you obtain the
green representation.
이것이 바로 단어의 표현입니다.
And that is your
word representation.
이해되셨나요?
Does that make sense?
네, 네.
Yeah, yeah.
좋은 질문입니다. 아주 좋은 질문이에요.
Yeah, great question,
great question.
질문은 v가 무엇을 의미하는지와
So the question is about
what does v correspond to
왜 여섯 개만 있는지에 관한 것입니다.
and why there's only six.
맞아요, 이 예시에서는 가능한 단어가 여섯 개뿐입니다.
So yes, in this example we only
have six possible words, which
어휘집의 크기가 여섯인 아주 단순한 예제가 되겠습니다.
is basically the vocabulary
size, just like a very toy
현실에서는 훨씬 더 많겠지만, 여기서는 단순화를 위해 소규모 예시입니다.
example, because in
practice there is many more.
이게 바로 언어에서 겪는 어려움 중 하나라고 볼 수 있겠죠.
So I guess that's one of the
challenges with language.
사실 단어는 다양한 형태로 변형될 수 있습니다.
So you can technically
have many variations
그래서 단어 단위로 텍스트를 토큰화하면
of words, which is why if
you take a word-level way
결국 어휘집이 상당히 커질 수 있습니다.
to divide your text into
tokens, you can end up
모든 단어의 변형을 모두 고려해줘야 하기 때문이죠.
with the vocabulary
that's very big,
그래서 어휘집이 커질 수밖에 없습니다.
because you need to account
for all the variations of given
모든 단어의 다양한 형태를 다 포함해야 하니까요.
words.
또 한 가지 짚어보고 싶은 점이 있습니다.
And the other thing
that I want to point out
예를 들어 어휘집 크기가 6이라고 해봅시다.
is, let's suppose you have
a vocabulary size of 6,
그리고 이 어휘집은 학습할 때 본
여섯 개의 단어로만 이루어졌다고 가정해봅시다.
and it's the six words that
you saw at training time.
그런데 만약에 추론할 때
어떤 일이 일어날까요?
But what happens if
at inference time
학습 중에는 본 적 없는 단어가
등장하면 어떻게 될까요?
you have a word that you have
not seen at training time?
이 경우에 보통 사람들이 하는 방법이 있습니다.
And so the answer for that
is typically what people do
일반적으로는 이를 위해
특정 자리를 남겨둡니다.
is they reserve a
spot for what they
이걸 흔히 언노운 토큰 또는
OOV(Out-Of-Vocabulary) 토큰이라고 부르죠.
call an unknown token or
out-of-vocabulary token,
쉽게 말하면, 이 토큰은
우리가 식별하지 못한 모든 것들을 담는 통이라고 볼 수 있습니다.
which is basically you can think
of it as a bucket for everything
즉, 우리가 식별할 수 없었던 것들은
이 언노운 토큰으로 처리됩니다.
that we were not
able to identify.
예를 들어, 추론할 때
식별하지 못한 토큰이 들어오면
So if let's suppose
at inference time
그런 토큰들은 모두
같은 표현, 즉 언노운 토큰 표현을 사용하게 됩니다.
you have a token that you
were not able to identify,
이렇게 언노운 토큰
표현으로 대체되는 것이죠.
they will all take
that representation,
즉, 언노운 토큰의
임베딩을 사용하게 됩니다.
which is the unknown
token representation.
이건 사실
단어 단위 토크나이저에서
And this is, by
the way, something
처리가 어렵다는 점이 있습니다.
that I guess the word-level
tokenizer has trouble to do,
왜냐하면 단어 단위에서는
OOV 토큰이 나올 확률이 매우 높기 때문이죠.
because you will have a
much bigger chance of having
아웃 오브 보캐뷸러리(OOV) 토큰이 많이 발생할 수 있습니다.
out-of-vocabulary tokens.
서브워드 단위에서는 그 확률이
훨씬 적어집니다.
Subword level will
have a lower chance.
그리고 문자 단위에서는
이런 OOV 문제가 거의 없습니다.
And then character
level, I guess,
즉, 문자 단위에서는
아예 이런 문제가 생기지 않습니다.
you don't have that problem.
이 설명이 궁금하신 내용에 답이 되었나요?
Does that answer your question?
네.
Yeah.
좋아요, 감사합니다.
Cool, yeah.
좋은 질문이었습니다.
Great, great question.
첫 번째 질문은, 언제 끝나는가입니다.
So first question
is, when you're done?
프록시 태스크에서 중요한 점은,
모델을 학습할 때
So the thing with the proxy task
is when you train your model,
사실 진짜 목표는,
정확히 다음 단어를 예측하는 것만은 아닙니다.
I guess your true objective
is to not really learn--
여기서는요.
I mean, in this case--
어떻게 하면 다음 단어를
예측할 수 있는지 배우는 것이죠.
to learn how to
predict the next word.
근본적인 목적은 의미 있는 표현을
얻는 데 있습니다.
Your objective is to have
meaningful representations.
하지만 실제로 우리가 할 수 있는 건
프록시 태스크의 손실을 모니터링하는 것입니다.
But what you can do
is to somehow track
여러분이 수행하는 프록시 태스크에 대한
손실 함수 값을 추적할 수 있습니다.
the loss function for the proxy
task that you're pursuing,
하지만 이 손실만 고려해서는 안 되고,
이게 최종 목표가 아니라는 점도 생각해야 합니다.
but then also taking into
consideration that this is not
이 손실 기준이 반드시 최종 목표는 아닙니다.
necessarily your end goal.
여기서 가장 합리적인 접근 방식 중 하나는
So I guess one
very reasonable way
모델이 수렴할 때까지
기다리는 것입니다.
of going about doing this is
just to wait until your model
즉, 모델이 수렴하는 시점을 보는 거죠.
converges.
여기서는 손실 값을 계속 추적하면서
So here, what you do
is you track the loss
이 손실이 어떻게 변화하는지 봅니다.
as a function of--
"에폭(epoch)"이라는 용어가 있는데,
이건 모델이 학습 데이터를 몇 번 봤는지를 의미합니다.
so there's this term "epoch,"
just how many times your model
모델이 학습 데이터를 얼마나 반복해서 보는지 나타내는 거죠.
sees the training set.
이렇게 다양한 손실 곡선들을 비교할 수 있습니다.
And so you compare
these different curves.
이 곡선이 수렴할 때가
보통 학습을 멈추기에 좋은 시점입니다.
And when this converges,
this is typically a good time
그때 학습을 멈추고,
해당 결과가 타당한지 확인하면 됩니다.
to stop the training process and
just see if that makes sense.
물론, 이 시점은 여러분의 다운스트림 태스크에 따라 다릅니다.
Depends on your downstream
task, of course.
하지만 이것이 한 가지 방법입니다.
But that's one.
두 번째 질문에 대해 말씀드리자면,
죄송하지만 다시 한 번 질문해주실 수 있나요?
So your second
question-- sorry, can you
두 번째 질문 다시 말씀해주시겠어요?
repeat the second question?
네, 좋은 질문입니다.
Yeah, yeah, oh, great question.
질문은, 생성 과정이 언제 끝나는지
어떻게 알 수 있냐는 것이었죠.
So the question is, how do you
know when the generation stops?
그렇지 않으면
생성이 끝나지 않을 겁니다.
I guess, otherwise
it will never stop.
네, 맞아요.
So yeah, exactly.
그래서 특별한 토큰을 사용합니다.
So you have some special tokens.
일반적으로는 end of sequence 토큰, 즉
시퀀스 종료 토큰이 사용됩니다.
Typically, you have end of
sequence, end of sequence.
보통 시퀀스 종료 토큰이 생성되면,
So typically when you have the
end of sequence token generated,
그때 생성이 멈추게 됩니다.
then it's when it stops.
좋습니다.
All right.
두 번째 질문은
은닉 레이어의 크기에 관한 것이었습니다.
So second question
was what informs
은닉 레이어의 크기는 어떻게 결정하나요?
the size of the hidden layer?
저는 이게 일종의 트레이드오프라고 생각합니다.
I would say it's a
trade-off, because you
임베딩이 충분히 풍부하게 표현되어야
want the embedding
to be rich enough
즉, 임베딩이 다운스트림 태스크에 충분히 정보를 줄 수 있어야 합니다.
that it can be informative
for your downstream task.
예를 들어, 어떤 방식으로든 문장의 임베딩을 얻고 싶다고 해봅시다.
So for instance, if
you want to somehow get
예를 들어 문장의 임베딩을 만들고 싶을 때,
an embedding of, let's
say, your sentence,
만약 아주 특화된, 다양한 결과를 요구하는 태스크를 하고 싶다면
and if you want to, let's
say, do a very, very
결과의 다양성이 큰 특수한 태스크를 한다고 하면,
specialized task, like with
a lot of different outcomes,
이를 잘 반영할 수 있는 벡터가 필요하니 더 큰 벡터가 필요할 수 있습니다.
maybe you want a vector that
recaptures that, so maybe you
반면, 만약 아주 단순한 태스크라면 더 작은 벡터도 괜찮을 수 있습니다.
want a bigger vector, but if
you had a very simple task,
작은 벡터가 더 적합할 수도 있죠.
maybe a smaller vector
might make sense.
즉, 은닉 차원의 크기는
So I guess the size of
your hidden dimension
이후에 처리하는 작업의 복잡도에도 영향을 미치게 됩니다.
also impacts the complexity of
whatever you're running after.
더 긴 벡터일수록 계산량이 많아지고,
Because of course, if
you have longer vectors,
추론 시에도 연산 비용이 증가할 수 있습니다.
you'll have more computation, so
your inference will be probably
즉, 추론 비용도 커집니다.
more expensive, et cetera.
이처럼 여러 가지 요소가 영향을 미칩니다.
So I guess there's
a lot of factors.
정리하자면, 첫 번째로는 다운스트림 태스크의 복잡성이 중요하고,
So I guess just to recap,
one is how complicated
다운스트림 태스크가 얼마나 복잡한지가 한 요소입니다.
your downstream task is.
두 번째는 레이턴시나 비용 등 각종 요구사항에 얼마나 민감한지도 영향을 줍니다.
Second one is how
sensitive are you
레이턴시, 비용 등 여러 요소에 민감한지도 중요합니다.
with latency, cost,
all these things.
결국 트레이드오프가 존재합니다.
So it's really a trade-off.
실제로는 보통
But out there you
would typically
수백에서 수천 차원 임베딩을 많이 사용합니다.
see embeddings of a pool
of hundreds or thousands.
물론 모델들이 점점 커지고 있기 때문에
Of course, these models,
they've been growing,
이 숫자는 바뀔 수 있습니다.
so this number may change.
하지만 대략 이 정도 크기라고 생각하면 됩니다.
But that's the
order of magnitude
이 정도 오더의 크기라고 보시면 됩니다.
that you're looking at.
맞아요.
Right.
실제적으로 경험에 근거한 수치입니다.
This is indeed empirical.
네, 그렇습니다.
Yeah, yeah.
다른 사람들이 찾아낸 결과에 의존해서 결정할 수도 있습니다.
I guess you can also
rely on what others found
그런 식으로 참고해서 정하면 됩니다.
and just go from that.
그런데 768 같은 숫자들은
많은 사람들이 일반적으로 사용하는 값입니다.
But 768, these numbers are
things that people typically
대부분 그렇게 선택하죠.
take.
좋습니다.
Cool, yeah.
좋은 질문입니다.
Great question.
질문은, 어떻게 같은 철자의 단어라도
다른 문맥에서 구분할 수 있느냐는 것이죠.
So the question is,
how can you distinguish
철자는 같지만 문맥이 다른 단어들을
어떻게 구분할 수 있을까요?
words that are spelled the
same but in different contexts?
아주 좋은 선행 질문이네요.
So you're way ahead of me.
이 내용이 바로 기본적인 내용입니다.
So this is basically the basics.
그리고 이제
이런 문제를 다루는 방법들을 살펴볼 겁니다.
And we're going
to tackle methods
즉, 단어를 문장 내에서 어떻게 문맥화할 수 있는지
해결하는 방법들을 배울 겁니다.
that can tackle these problems
of just contextualizing
즉, 단어를 문장 안에서 어떻게 해석하는지 다루게 됩니다.
the word in the sentence.
곧 그 부분을 자세히 살펴보겠습니다.
So yeah, so we'll
see that in a bit.
좋습니다.
Cool.
지금 시간이 좀 지연되고 있네요.
I'm not on time.
그래서 좀 더 빠르게 진행하겠습니다.
So I'll try to get moving.
지금까지 우리가 한 것은
토큰의 표현을 어떻게 학습할 수 있는지 살펴본 것이었습니다.
So OK, so now what
we did was see
토큰의 표현을
어떻게 학습할 수 있는지 다뤘죠.
how we could learn
representations of tokens.
하지만 어떤 경우에는 여러분이
문장이나 텍스트의 표현도 얻고 싶을 수 있습니다.
But I guess you may also
want to get representations
즉, 문장이나 텍스트 조각의
표현을 얻고 싶을 수도 있겠습니다.
of sentences or pieces of text.
이전에 본 방식을 가지고 이런 걸 아주 단순하게 하려면,
So one very naive way to do
that with what we saw before
예를 들어 단어 표현들을 평균 내는 방법이 있겠죠.
is to take something like
the average of words,
즉, 단어 임베딩의 평균을 내는 방식입니다.
let's say, the word
representations.
하지만 이 방법의 문제는
의미를 많이 잃게 된다는 겁니다.
But the problem is you
lose a lot of meaning,
순서도 잃고, 많은 정보가 사라집니다.
you lose the order, you lose--
또 여기서도 아주 잘 지적해주셨듯이,
and I guess here, I think
you pointed out very well,
우리가 얻는 표현들은
토큰의 위치와 상관없이 토큰에 대한 표현이죠.
the representations
that you learn
즉, 어디에 있든지간에 토큰별로 표현이 동일하게 할당됩니다.
are token-specific, regardless
of where they're at.
그래서 이 때문에 이런 순차적인 특성을 포착할 수 있는
모델 계열이 필요합니다.
So that's why we have
a class of models
이런 모델들은 텍스트가
어떻게 순차적으로 등장하는지를 잡아내는 데 목적이 있습니다.
that aim at capturing the
sequential nature of how
즉, 텍스트가 나타나는 순서를 반영하는 것이죠.
text appears.
이제 RNN에 대해 이야기해보겠습니다.
RNN은 Recurrent Neural Network, 즉 순환 신경망을 의미합니다.
So we're going to talk
about RNNs, which stands
Recurrent Neural Network를 줄여서 RNN이라고 부릅니다.
for Recurrent Neural Network.
RNN은 단어를 한 번에 하나씩 처리하는 대신,
So what RNNs do is,
instead of processing words
단어를 따로따로 처리하기보다는,
one at a time, what
they do is they
지금까지의 문장에 대한 은닉 표현(hidden representation)을 유지하면서,
keep a hidden representation
of the sentence so far,
토큰을 하나씩 차례대로 고려하는 방식입니다.
and they consider
tokens one at a time.
제가 앞서 언급했듯이,
이 방식은 사실 상당히 오래전에 도입되었습니다.
So as I mentioned before,
this technique was actually
즉, 80년대에 처음 소개된 기법입니다.
introduced a fair amount of
time ago, so in the '80s.
이 모델은 단어, 즉 토큰이 등장한 순서를 고려합니다.
And what this model does is
it takes into consideration
단어 또는 토큰이 등장한 순서 자체를 모델이 반영한다는 것이죠.
the order at which words
appeared or tokens appeared.
이 예시에서처럼, 문장의 맨 처음부터 처리하기 시작합니다.
And so in this
example, you start the,
문장 맨 앞에서부터 차례로 처리하게 되는 것이죠.
I guess, processing at the
very beginning of the sentence.
처음에는 더미(dummmy) 은닉 상태, 예를 들면 A라는 것을 가집니다.
You have some dummy hidden
states that is called A,
보통 A나 H 등으로 표기하며,
이것을 은닉 상태(hidden state)라고 부릅니다.
typically denoted
A or H. It's called
은닉 상태, 활성화(activation), 또는 때로는 컨텍스트 벡터(context vector)라고도 합니다.
the hidden state, activation, or
even sometimes a context vector.
그리고 이 은닉 상태를 입력받는 어떤 모듈이 있습니다.
And you have some
kind of a module that
지금까지의 은닉 상태와
takes into account the
hidden state so far
그리고 현재 시점 t, 여기서는 1번째 시점의 단어를 함께 고려합니다.
and the word at time step
t, so here time step 1.
이렇게 하면 문장의 지금까지 의미와
So here what it does is it takes
in the meaning of the sentence
현재 입력된 단어 정보를 함께 반영합니다.
so far and takes
into consideration
즉, 현재 등장한 단어를 고려하게 됩니다.
the word that is happening now.
그리고 이렇게 얻은 출력 벡터(output vector)를
And it produces an
output vector that
다음 단어를 예측하는 데 사용할 수 있습니다.
here can be used to try
to predict the next word.
예를 들어, 이곳에 은닉 상태와
So for instance here we
have this hidden state
단어의 표현이 함께 있습니다.
and the representation
of the word
그리고 여기서 행렬 곱셈(matrix multiplication)이 발생합니다.
that then you have some
matrix multiplications
이 파란색 박스 안에서 연산이 이루어집니다.
in this blue box.
그리고 다시 출력 벡터가 만들어지면,
And you have an
output vector that you
이를 이용해서 다음 단어를 예측하도록 학습합니다.
try to train on
predicting the next words.
그리고 이렇게 지금까지의 은닉 상태들을 유지하면서
이 과정을 계속 반복합니다.
And then you keep on
doing that by keeping
이렇게 해서 이 은닉 상태들을 추적하게 됩니다.
track of these hidden states.
그리고 이런 과정을 반복하게 됩니다.
And so you repeat the process.
이 은닉 상태를 어떻게 해석할 수 있을까요?
And I guess the way you would
interpret these hidden states
이 은닉 상태는 지금까지 처리한
시퀀스를 나타내는 표현입니다.
is it's a representation of
the sequence process so far.
RNN의 장점은 이제 단어의 순서가 중요한 요소가 되었다는 점입니다.
So the good thing with RNNs
is now the word order matters.
또한 문장을 더 자연스럽게
인코딩할 수 있습니다.
And you're also able
to encode the sentence
보다 자연스러운 방식으로 문장을 표현할 수 있죠.
in a more natural way.
이제 대략적으로 어떻게 동작하는지 살펴보겠습니다.
So let's see roughly
how it works.
똑같은 예시를 사용해보겠습니다.
So we have the same
favorite example,
"so cute teddy bear is reading"이라는 예시입니다.
so cute teddy bear is reading.
우선 토큰 A가 있다고 합시다.
이 토큰을 원-핫 인코딩 벡터로 준비합니다.
So you would have the token
A. You want one-hot encoding
그 벡터를 사용하는 것이죠.
vector.
이 벡터를 신경망에 입력합니다.
You pass it through
your network.
그리고 은닉 상태를 계산합니다.
You compute the hidden state.
이제 cute라는 단어를 예측하려고 합니다.
You try to predict cute.
그리고 다시 은닉 상태를 추적합니다.
But then you keep track
of the hidden state.
그 은닉 상태를 다음 모듈에 입력합니다.
And then you input that
into another module.
그리고 다음 단어들도 함께 고려하게 됩니다.
And then you also
consider the next words.
즉, 단어 자체뿐 아니라 지금까지의
문장 은닉 상태도 활용하는 것이죠.
So you consider not only the
word itself, but also the hidden
이렇게 현재까지의 문장 은닉 상태를 함께 고려합니다.
state of this sentence so far.
그리고 다시 다음 단어를 예측하는 과정을
계속 반복합니다.
And you try to predict the next
word again, and again and again.
이것이 바로 RNN입니다.
So this is RNN.
RNN은 여러 작업에 사용되었습니다.
So RNNs were used
for a bunch of tasks,
이제 이전에 봤던 그 카테고리와 연결해보면
and just like mapping that
back to the categories
이전에 봤던 분류 유형과 연관지을 수 있습니다.
that we saw before.
분류 작업의 경우에는
For classification
purposes, you can basically
문장의 마지막 단어의
은닉 상태를 사용할 수 있습니다.
use the hidden state of the
last word in your sentence.
예를 들어,
For instance, if
you want to predict
리뷰의 감정 분석처럼
결과를 예측하고 싶다면
like the sentiment
of a review, you
여기서는 마지막 벡터를 활용하게 됩니다.
would take basically
the last vector here
그리고 이 마지막 벡터를
예측 공간에 투영해서 사용합니다.
and try to project
it into the space
즉, 여러분이 예측하고자 하는 라벨 또는 클래스의 공간으로
이 벡터를 투영하는 것이죠.
of the predictions or the labels
that you want to predict on.
예를 들어 긍정인지 부정인지 예측하고 싶다면,
So for instance, if you
want positive or negative,
이 벡터를 해당 클래스 공간에 투영해서
결과를 얻을 수 있습니다.
you basically project that
vector onto that space.
여기서 그런 방식으로 활용할 수 있습니다.
You can do that here.
다중 분류의 경우에도 마찬가지로,
For multi-classification,
so you would basically
관심 있는 토큰의 표현을 선택하고,
have the representation
of the token of interest,
그 벡터를 클래스 공간에 투영합니다.
and you would project that.
생성(generation) 태스크의 경우에는,
Or for generation,
you would basically
전체 소스 텍스트를 처리한 다음,
process the whole
source text, and then
컨텍스트 벡터, 즉
have a context vector, a.k.a.
액티베이션 벡터, 또는
activation vector, a.k.a.
처리가 끝난 뒤의 은닉 상태를 얻게 됩니다.
hidden state at the
end of your processing,
이 벡터를 활용해서 최종 출력값을 디코딩하게 됩니다.
which will then be used to
decode the output prediction.
이렇게 각각의 태스크에서 RNN을 활용할 수 있습니다.
So this is how you would use
an RNN for each of these tasks.
최근에는 RNN에 대해 많이 들어볼 수 없는 이유가 있습니다.
So the reason why you have not
really heard of RNNs these days
RNN에도 장점이 있긴 했지만, 단점이 훨씬 많았기 때문입니다.
is because they had some
pros, but a lot of cons.
그 단점 중 하나는 문장의 의미가
So one of the cons is that
the meaning of the sentence
오로지 이 은닉 상태 하나에
모두 담긴다는 점입니다.
is basically solely encapsulated
into this hidden state.
이렇게 되면 장기 의존성(long-range dependencies) 문제가 발생합니다.
So you have this problem
of long-range dependencies,
즉, 모델이 이전 내용을
which basically impacts your
ability to quote, unquote,
'기억한다'고 표현하는 능력에
제약이 생깁니다.
"remember" what the
model saw in the past,
그래서 이 문제를 해결하려는 또 다른 종류의 모델이 등장하게 되었고,
which is why you have another
class of models that try
그들이 RNN의 한계를 극복하려 했습니다.
to build on RNNs.
그 대표적인 예가 LSTM, 즉 Long Short-Term Memory입니다.
So this one is called LSTMs,
Long Short-Term Memory.
이 구조의 목표는 모델이
And the goal of that extension
is to have the way to somehow
중요한 정보, 즉 반드시 '기억'해야 하는 내용을
keep track of the things that
are quote, unquote, "important"
추가적으로 추적할 수 있도록 하는 것입니다.
to remember, on top of the
hidden state that we talked
이렇게 은닉 상태 외에도 중요 정보를 다룹니다.
about.
여기에서 a_t는 액티베이션을 의미합니다.
So here you have a of t,
which is your activation,
기본적으로 지금까지의 시퀀스가
여기에 인코딩되어 있습니다.
basically the sequence
so far encoded in there.
그리고 또 다른 값이 존재하는데
And then you have
another quantity
여러분이 추적해야 할 값으로,
셀 상태라고 불립니다.
that you track that is
called the cell state.
여기서는 c로 표기합니다.
It's denoted c here.
이 구조는 그 부분을 개선하는 것을
목표로 하고 있습니다.
So this architecture aims
at improving that piece,
하지만 이 구조도
완벽하지는 않았습니다.
but I guess it was
not perfect either.
어쨌든 그게 주요한 문제였고,
But yeah, so that
was the main issue
RNN 기반 방법의 문제는,
of RNN-based methods,
which is that they
이전 정보를 잊어버리는
현상이 있다는 점입니다.
have this issue of forgetting
what was in the past.
논문 등에서는 이런 현상을
So you will see
in the literature
"그래디언트 소실(vanishing gradient)"이라고 부릅니다.
that this phenomenon is
called vanishing gradient.
왜 이런 이름이 붙었는지 살펴보면―
And the reason why it's called
that way-- so I know we're
시간이 거의 다 됐지만, 그 부분만
간단히 설명하겠습니다.
running out of time, but I'm
going to just explain that part.
예를 들어 마지막 단어를 예측하려면
So in order for you to predict,
let's say, the last words,
사실상 모든 은닉 상태에
의존하게 됩니다.
you're basically dependent
on every hidden state
이전의 은닉 상태들이 다 중요합니다.
that came before that.
여기까지 괜찮으신가요?
So far so good?
그리고 모델의 가중치를
업데이트하려고 할 때,
And so whenever you want to
update the weights of your model
예측값이 실제값과 일치하도록
만들어야 하겠죠.
to match the prediction here
with the actual prediction, when
이때 역전파를 하게 되면,
어떤 식으로든
you do the back
propagation, you somehow
여기 있는 값이
단순히 이 계산뿐만 아니라,
need to take into account that
the value here is basically
다른 계산의 결과도
같이 반영되어야 합니다.
not only a matter
of this computation,
즉, 이런 연산들이
순차적으로 일어난 결과입니다.
but also this computation
or this computation
모두 순차적으로 진행된 연산들이죠.
that basically happened
in a sequential manner.
그래서 여러분이
"시간을 따라 역전파"를 시도하게 됩니다.
So you have this phenomenon
of trying to, I guess,
이걸 흔히 '시간을 따라 역전파한다'고 합니다.
back-propagate through time.
그런데 실제로
But the problem is,
in practice when
수식으로 써보면
you write that down-- so
it's a very ugly formula.
사실 굉장히 복잡하게 보이고,
But when you write
that down, it ends up
실제로는 여러 값들의 곱셈 결과로
표현됩니다.
being a product of a
bunch of quantities
이 값이 1보다 크면, 기울기가 폭발하게 됩니다.
that can-- so if it's greater
than 1, then it's exploding.
1보다 작으면, 기울기가 사라집니다.
If it's less than
1, it's vanishing.
1보다 작은 값들을 계속 곱하면,
Because if you multiply a lot
of things that are less than 1,
결국 0에 가까워집니다.
it just goes to 0.
만약 업데이트해야 하는 값이
So I guess if you have
something that you're
계속 0으로 수렴한다면,
trying to update that
goes to 0, basically
업데이트 자체가 제대로 이루어지지 않습니다.
you have trouble just
doing your updates.
이게 바로 전체적인 직관입니다.
So that's a
high-level intuition.
이 내용이 오늘 강의의 핵심은 아닙니다.
This is not the
focus of this class,
그래서 이 복잡한 수식까지는
which is why I'm not
going into the detail
자세하게 다루지 않을게요.
of this ugly formulas.
하지만 여러분이 이런 개념을 이해했으면 좋겠습니다.
But I hope you get the idea
that for remembering things
과거 정보를 기억하는 데에는
from the past, it's
not doing a great job,
이런 순차적인 특성 때문에 잘 작동하지 않습니다.
because of this sequential,
I guess, characteristic.
이해가 되셨나요?
Does that make sense?
자, 이제 다음 내용을 보면 조금 더 이해가 될 겁니다.
OK, I hope the next thing
will make a bit more sense.
그 전에, 지금까지 다룬 내용을 정리하겠습니다.
But before that, I'll
just recap what we saw.
우리의 목표는 텍스트를 표현하는 것입니다.
So our goal is to
represent text.
먼저 워드나 토큰을 어떻게 표현할지 고민했고,
So we first started
with representing
이때 Word2vec 방식을 사용했습니다.
words or tokens, which was what
we tried to do with Word2vec.
Word2vec은 프록시 태스크를 활용해서
And we saw that it was a good
way to leverage proxy tasks
이러한 표현을 학습한다는 장점이 있습니다.
to learn this representation.
하지만 여러 가지 한계도 있었습니다.
But we had a bunch
of limitations.
그 중 하나가, 여러분이 언급해 준 것처럼,
And one of them
that you mentioned
문맥을 반영하지 못한다는 점이었습니다.
was that this was not
aware of the context.
그리고 또 하나는 단어 순서를 반영하지 않는다는 점이죠.
And also the word
order didn't count.
그래서 또 다른 방식의 방법들이 등장했는데,
And so you have this
other class of methods
이들은 단어 자체만이 아니라
that is able to take into
consideration the words,
문맥도 고려하려 하지만,
but then they have some
trouble keeping track of things
시퀀스가 길어질수록 정보를 잘 기억하지 못하는 문제가 있습니다.
when the sequence
gets very long.
그리고 여기서 등장하는 문제가 바로 기울기 소실 문제입니다.
And you have this problem
of vanishing gradients
또는 긴 범위의 의존성 문제라고도 하죠.
or long-range dependencies.
이 용어가 나오면,
So whenever you
see this term, it's
방금 설명한 문제를 의미하는 것입니다.
basically referring to that.
또 한 가지 언급하지 않은 점이 있는데,
And also another thing
that I have not mentioned,
계산이 매우 느립니다.
but the computations
are very slow.
따라서 이런 모델을 학습시킬 때,
So when you want to train
these models, at training time,
특정 단어를 예측하려면
in order to predict
this word, you basically
이전에 있던 모든 은닉 상태를 계산해야 합니다.
need to compute all these
hidden states before.
그래서 시퀀스가 아주 길어지면,
So when your sequence
gets very long,
계산에 정말 많은 시간이 소요됩니다.
it just takes a very long time.
이런 여러 가지 이유로, 즉 어떤 이유로냐면,
So for all of these reasons,
for I guess what reason.
모델이 과거의 정보를 기억하기 어려운 점을 보완하기 위해
So for the fact that the model
has trouble remembering things
더 직접적인 연결을 시도하게 됩니다.
from the past, people have tried
having more direct connections
즉, 과거의 정보와 현재를 더 직접적으로 연결하는 것이죠.
between something and
the thing from the past,
이것이 바로 어텐션의 핵심 아이디어입니다.
and this is the idea
behind attention.
어텐션은
So what attention
does is it tries
우리가 예측하고자 하는 항목과
to have a direct link between
what we're trying to predict
과거의 어떤 것 사이에 직접적인 연결을 만들어냅니다.
and something from the past.
예를 들어,
So in this example,
let's suppose
제가 영어 문장을
I'm trying to translate
an English sentence
프랑스어로 번역한다고 가정해봅시다.
into a French one.
여기서는 입력 문장이 주어지고,
So here I guess the
input sentence is given.
은닉 상태를 계산하게 됩니다.
I'm computing the hidden state.
단어를 하나씩 처리하면서,
I'm processing
words one at a time.
이것이 전통적인 RNN 구조인 거죠.
This is my traditional RNN.
예를 들면 "a cute teddy bear is reading." 같은 문장입니다.
So "a cute teddy
bear is reading."
여기서는 은닉 상태를 얻고, 그걸 디코딩하게 됩니다.
So here I have a hidden
state that I'm then decoding.
이제 번역문에서 다음 단어를
And you can imagine
that when wanting
생성하려고 할 때를 생각해볼 수 있습니다.
to generate the next
word of my translation,
내가 어떤 단어를 예측하려고 하는지 알 수 있다면 정말 좋겠죠.
it would be great if I knew
what word I'm trying to predict.
다른 말로 하면,
Or in other words,
it would be great
입력 텍스트의 특정 부분을 살짝 들여다볼 수 있다면 더 좋을 겁니다.
if I could take a peek at a
certain area of the input text.
그래서 어텐션의 핵심 아이디어는
So the idea behind
attention is to have
우리가 예측하려는 것과
a direct link between what
you're trying to predict
이전 정보 사이에 직접적인 연결고리를 만드는 것입니다.
and things before.
이것이 바로 어텐션의 기본 개념입니다.
This is the idea
behind attention.
이 어텐션 개념은 2014년에 처음 도입됐습니다.
And so it was
introduced in 2014.
그리고 이 방법은
And yeah, again, this
is trying to solve
이런 장기 의존성(long-range dependency) 문제를 해결하려는 시도이기도 합니다.
for these long-range
dependency issues.
그래서 이런 예시에서도 저희는 이 접근법을 적용하고 싶죠.
And so yeah, this example
we want to do that.
이 개념은 사실 이번 강의에서 아주 중요한 핵심이 될 겁니다.
And this concept is going to
actually be key for this class.
강의에서 앞으로 보겠지만, 어텐션 메커니즘이
Because we're going to see
that the attention mechanism is
여러 요소들이 동작하도록 만드는
the thing that is going
to make everything--
핵심 원리라는 걸 알 수 있을 겁니다.
I mean, most of the things work.
실제로 이것이 트랜스포머 논문이
And this is actually
the main principle
기반하고 있는 핵심 원리입니다.
that the transformer
paper relies on.
그리고 트랜스포머는 이번 수업에서 다룰
So the transformer, which
is the core architecture
중심적인 아키텍처로,
that we will see in this
class, has been introduced
2017년 "Attention is All You Need"라는 논문에서
or was introduced in
2017 in this paper named
처음 제안됐습니다.
Attention is All You Need.
논문 제목에서 알 수 있듯이, 저자들은 이 부분에만 집중하려고 했고,
So even from the title, you
can see that the authors wanted
어텐션 메커니즘만으로 접근하고자 했습니다.
to just rely on that part.
논문 저자들이 시도한 것은
So what the authors
tried to do was
이런 순차적인 처리 방식을 벗어나서,
to move away from this
sequential way of processing
모델이 텍스트의 모든 부분과 한 번에 직접 연결될 수 있도록 한 것입니다.
the text, and instead
let the model just
바로 이것을 셀프 어텐션(self-attention)이라고 합니다.
have direct connections with
all parts of the text at once.
이 셀프 어텐션을 번역 과제 등에 적용해본 결과
So that is called
self-attention.
아주 좋은 성능을 낸다는 것을 확인했습니다.
So they tried that
on translation tasks.
[번역 실패] And they just realized that it was giving great results.
And they just realized that
it was giving great results.
그러면 우리가 계속 사용하고 있는 예시로 돌아가 보겠습니다.
So back to the example
that we're still using,
귀여운 테디베어가 책을 읽고 있다,라고 할 때,
여기서는 이렇게 설명할 수 있습니다.
a cute teddy bear is reading
Here what we would say
테디베어 토큰의 표현을 계산하기 위해서는
is that in order to
compute the representation
이제 테디베어라는 토큰의 표현을 구하려면
of the token teddy
bear, we're going
시퀀스 안의 모든 다른 토큰을 한 번에 살펴봐야 합니다.
to look at all the other
tokens in the sequence at once,
그리고 각 토큰과 직접 연결되는 방식입니다.
and directly with direct links.
그러니까 아까 질문하신 부분으로 다시 돌아가서,
So I guess back to
your question-- here,
이 예시에서는 테디베어에 대한 표현이
we would have a
representation of teddy bear
그 토큰이 포함된 문맥에 따라 고유하게 결정된다고 할 수 있습니다.
that would be unique to the
context that it is part of.
즉, 여러분이 bank라는 단어를 riverbank에서 쓸 때와 robbing a bank에서 쓸 때처럼,
So back to your question about
riverbank and robbing a bank,
bank라는 단어가 서로 다른 표현을 갖게 되는 것이죠.
like here the bank would have
different representations.
바로 이런 아이디어입니다.
So this is the idea.
이 개념이 대략적으로 이해가 되시나요?
I guess, does the idea
roughly make sense?
다시 한번 말씀드리지만, 이것이 바로 셀프 어텐션 메커니즘입니다.
And again, this is called
the self-attention mechanism.
Afshine, 지금 시간 얼마나 남았나요?
Afshine, how am I doing on time?
8분 남았습니다.
8.
8분 남았나요?
I have 8?
네, 좋습니다.
OK, cool.
자, 다시, 이게 핵심입니다.
OK, so this is the idea.
이제 여기서 더 중요한 용어나 개념을 몇 가지 소개하겠습니다.
So now I'm going
to just introduce
새로운 용어들이지만
another set of ideas
which is more terminology
굉장히 중요한 내용입니다.
but is going to
be very important.
어떤 것을 다른 것의 관점에서 표현하고 싶을 때는
So when you want to express
something in terms of something
query, key, value 즉 Q, K, V라는 용어를 사용합니다.
else, we use the words "query,"
"key," and "value," Q, K and V.
이 예시에서 우리의 목표는
So in this example, our
goal is to figure out
쿼리인 테디베어가 어떤 다른 토큰들과 더 비슷한지 찾는 것입니다.
what other tokens is the query
teddy bear more similar to.
여기서는 쿼리가 주어졌을 때
So here the question
is, OK, you have a query
다른 토큰들 중에서 무엇이 가장 유사한지 살펴보는 것이죠.
and you want to see what
other tokens are most similar.
그래서 우리가 할 일은
And so what you're
going to do is
모든 다른 토큰들을, 즉
to look at all the other
tokens which are basically
이 토큰들은 키와 값으로 구성되어 있습니다.
composed of keys and values.
그래서 이제 쿼리와 키를 비교해서
So we're going to compare
the query to the key
쿼리와 특정 키가 얼마나 비슷한지
정량화하게 됩니다.
to quantify how similar your
query is to a given key,
그리고 해당하는 값을 가져오죠.
and take the
corresponding value.
이 예시에선
이 과정을 직접 살펴보겠습니다.
So we'll see that
in this example,
예를 들어 teddy bear를
다른 모든 토큰으로 표현하려고 한다고 가정해봅시다.
so let's suppose you want to
express teddy bear in terms
즉, 다른 모든 것들로 teddy bear를 표현하는 거죠.
of everything else.
여기서 여러분이 해야 할 일은
What you're going
to do is you're
쿼리인 teddy bear를 가지고
going to take the
query teddy bear,
이 쿼리를 다른 모든 키들과
비교해보는 것입니다.
and you're going to compare that
query with all the other keys
어떤 요소가 가장 유사한지
확인하게 됩니다.
to see which element
is most similar,
그리고 더 유사한 것일수록
가중치를 더 많이 두고,
and then weight the
more similar ones
그 가중치에 해당하는 값을 가져오게 됩니다.
and take their associated value.
이것이 이런 방식이 전반적으로 어떻게 동작하는지에 대한 큰 그림입니다.
So that's a very high level
idea of how these things are.
물론, 실제로 이 과정이 어떻게 동작하는지
자세히 살펴볼 것입니다.
Of course, we're going to
see exactly how they work.
하지만 기본적인 아이디어는 이렇다는 점 기억하세요.
But that's the general idea.
네, 좋습니다.
OK, cool.
이제 쿼리, 키, 값에 관해 이야기했으니,
And speaking of query
and key and value,
이렇게 쿼리, 키, 값으로 표현하는 이점도 있습니다.
we will also see that one
benefit of expressing things
이 방식으로 하면
this way is that we
can express doing
전체 시퀀스에 대해 셀프 어텐션 연산을
this self-attention computation
across the whole sequence
행렬 형태로 표현할 수 있습니다.
in a matrix format.
그리고 GPU는 행렬 연산에 특화되어 있습니다.
And GPUs love matrices.
그래서 우리가 가진 하드웨어에 정말 잘 맞는 방식이죠.
So it's really made for
the hardware that we have.
또 방금 언급한 내용은
And I guess what
I mentioned here
소프트맥스 형태로 표현할 수 있습니다.
can be expressed in
a form of softmax
쿼리와 키 간의 소프트맥스 연산인데,
이는 각 값에 얼마의 가중치를 둘지 정하는 방식입니다.
of the query and the key,
which is basically a way
이런 식으로 어느 값이 더 중요한지
가중치를 얻을 수 있습니다.
to get some kinds of
weights of which values
값이 더 중요할수록 가중치가 커지겠죠.
will be more important.
예를 들어, 어떤 값이 더 중요하다면
So for instance, if a
value is more important,
더 중요한 값에는 더 큰 가중치가 할당됩니다.
you have bigger weight.
그리고 덜 중요한 값에는
And another one will
be less important,
더 작은 가중치가 할당됩니다.
you'll have a smaller weight.
이 가중치를 value에 곱해줍니다.
And you basically multiply
that by the value.
걱정하지 마세요. 곧 자세한 예시를 보여드리겠습니다.
So don't worry, we'll have
a detailed example after.
아직 추상적으로 느껴진다면 너무 걱정하지 않으셔도 됩니다.
So if it still feels very
high-level fuzzy, don't worry.
곧 자세하게 하나씩 설명드릴게요.
We'll have a
detailed walkthrough.
이렇게 동작하는 방식입니다.
And yes, so this
is how it works.
좋습니다.
OK, cool.
셀프 어텐션에 대해 질문 있으신가요?
Any questions on what
self-attention is?
네.
Yeah.
좋은 질문이에요.
Great, great question.
질문은 value와 key가 무엇이냐는 것이군요.
So the question is, what
is value, what is key?
그리고 어떻게 얻는지도 궁금하신 거죠?
I guess, how to get those?
각각이 어떤 의미인지 설명드릴게요.
What do they mean?
먼저 이 값들은 모두 학습된다는 점을 말씀드리고 싶습니다.
So first of all, I just want
to say that these quantities,
즉, 여러분이 직접 값을 고정하는 것이 아닙니다.
they are learned.
직접 설정하는 게 아닙니다.
So you are not fixing them.
하지만 해석 관점에서는,
But from an
interpretation standpoint,
key는 어떤 것이 쿼리와 가장 비슷한지 찾는 데 사용된다고 볼 수 있습니다.
you can interpret
that the key is there
즉, 쿼리와 가장 유사한 key를 찾는 역할이죠.
for you to figure out which one
is most similar to the query.
value는 실제 그 요소와 연관된 값을 의미합니다.
And the value is
the actual value
실제로 그 요소에 할당된 값을 나타내는 거죠.
that is associated
with that element.
여기서, 우리가 표현하고 싶은 것은
So here, you will have
something like you
모든 value들로 표현된다는 점입니다.
want to express this in
terms of all the values.
즉, 가중평균의 가중치는
So the weights in
your weighted average
기본적으로 쿼리와 key의 내적(dot product)으로 결정됩니다.
will be basically the
dot product between--
쿼리와 key 사이의 내적이죠.
basically-- between
the query and the key.
그리고 value는 실제로 사용할 벡터 값이 됩니다.
And the value will be the
actual vector that you will use.
다시 한 번 말씀드리지만, 이런 값들 모두가 학습됩니다.
But again, these
things are learned.
그리고 제가 아직 말씀드리지 않은 게 하나 있는데요,
And something I
have not mentioned,
하지만 여러분이 방금 잘 짚어주셨으니,
but you mentioned it
correctly, so we're
이제 실제로 이런 값들을 얻기 위해 프로젝션을 적용하게 됩니다.
going to actually do projections
to obtain these quantities.
그리고 이 프로젝션도 모델이 학습을 통해서 결정하게 됩니다.
And these projections are
actually learned by the model.
좋습니다?
That's good?
네, 좋습니다.
OK, cool.
자, 그럼 이제 15분 정도 남았으니,
So with that, we have
15 minutes, right,
아키텍처에 대해 이야기해보겠습니다.
to talk about the architecture.
네, 그러면 아주 전체적인 구조부터 살펴보면,
OK, so at a very
high level, in order
셀프 어텐션 메커니즘을 구현하기 위해서,
to make the self-attention
mechanism happen,
논문 저자들은 하나의 아키텍처를 제안하는데요,
the authors propose
an architecture
이 아키텍처는 크게 두 부분으로 나뉩니다. 바로 왼쪽의 인코더와
that is composed of two
parts, an encoder, which
오른쪽에 위치한 디코더입니다.
is on the left
side, and a decoder,
디코더는 오른쪽에 있습니다.
which is on the right side.
이 구조가 처음 적용된 대표적인 예가 바로 번역입니다.
So the application that
they have is translation.
인코더를 통과하는 입력은
So what will go
through the encoder
여러분이 번역하고자 하는 원문, 즉 소스 언어의 텍스트입니다.
is the input text in
your source language.
그리고 디코더를 통과하는 것은
And what is going to
go through the decoder
여러분이 예측하려는 타겟 언어 문장입니다.
is the target language
that you're predicting.
전체적인 아이디어는,
So the high-level
idea is you're going
입력 텍스트를 인코더에 통과시켜서 의미 있는 임베딩을 얻는 것입니다.
to compute meaningful
embeddings from your input text
인코더를 거치면서 임베딩이 만들어집니다.
by passing them
through the encoder.
그리고 여기에서 셀프 어텐션 메커니즘이 작동해야 합니다.
And you want that self-attention
mechanism to apply,
즉, 각 토큰의 표현이
meaning you want to compute
representations of each token
다른 토큰들과의 관계를 반영하도록 만드는 것입니다.
as a function of others.
이때 사용하는 것이 바로 어텐션 레이어입니다.
And you do that by using a layer
called the attention layer.
멀티헤드 어텐션 레이어가 대표적인데,
So multi-head attention
layer, but multi-head
멀티헤드는 이 계산을 여러 방식으로 병렬적으로
is just doing this
computation in different ways
수행해서 모델이 다양한 표현이나
to just allow the model to
learn different representations
다양한 프로젝션을 학습할 수 있도록 도와줍니다.
or different projections.
여기서 핵심 아이디어는, 여러분이 입력 텍스트를 넣는다는 것입니다.
But the idea here is you are
going to input your input text,
그리고 입력 텍스트 안의 모든 토큰들이
and all the tokens
in your input text
서로를 참조하게 됩니다.
are going to attend
to one another.
예를 들어, "a cute teddy bear is reading"라는 문장이 있다면
So for instance, a cute
teddy bear is reading,
이 텍스트의 모든 토큰에 대한 표현을
you are going to compute
the representation
모두 계산하게 되는 거죠.
of all the tokens in
this text basically
각 토큰은 다른 토큰들을 함수처럼 이용해서 표현을 만듭니다.
as a function of others.
이 과정은 인코더에서 진행되며,
And you're going to do that
with the encoder, so here
여기서 멀티헤드 어텐션이 사용됩니다.
with the multi-head attention.
그리고 그다음에는 피드포워드 레이어가 있습니다.
And then you have a
feedforward layer,
이 레이어는 모델이 또 다른 방식의 표현을 학습하도록 도와줍니다.
which is just to
let the model learn
즉, 또 다른 종류의 프로젝션을 학습하는 거죠.
another kind of projection.
이렇게 해서 여러분이 얻게 되는 것은
And what you're going
to obtain at the end
인코딩 과정이 끝났을 때
of your encoding process
is rich representations
입력 문장의 각 토큰에 대한 풍부한 표현입니다.
of the tokens from
the input sentence.
여기까지 괜찮으신가요?
So far, so good?
이제 실제 목표는 입력 문장을 번역하는 것입니다.
But now your goal is to actually
translate the input sentence.
그래서 여러분이 해야 할 일은 번역을 시작하는 건데요,
So what you're going to do
is to start your translation
예를 들어 문장 시작 토큰에서 시작한다고 해봅시다.
with, let's suppose, the
beginning of sentence token,
즉, 첫 번째 토큰이 되는 거죠.
so your first token.
이제 입력 문장에서 생성한 모든 표현을
And what you're going to do
is use all the representations
활용해서
from your input
sentence in order
다음에 무엇을 예측할지 판단하는 데 사용하는 겁니다.
to figure out what
to predict next.
제가 방금 설명한 부분이 바로 크로스 어텐션 레이어입니다.
So this what I just said is
the cross-attention layer,
이 레이어가 두 번째에 해당하는 부분이고,
which is the one that is
the second, so this one,
바로 이 부분인데요,
which basically--
화살표가 보이실지 모르겠지만,
I'm not sure if
you see the arrows,
인코더에서 나오는 화살표가 두 개 있고,
but there are two arrows
coming from the encoder, one
디코더에서 나오는 화살표가 하나 더 있습니다.
arrow coming from the decoder.
혹시 디코더에서 나오는 화살표가 무엇을 의미하는지 아시는 분 있나요?
Can anyone tell me what
the arrow from the decoder
무엇을 나타내는지 아시겠나요?
represents?
디코더가 쿼리, 키, 값 중 어떤 역할일까요?
Is decoder a query key or value?
아마 1/3, 즉 33%의 확률이겠네요.
I guess there is 1
over 3, 33% chance.
누가 한번 답해볼까요?
Who wants to try?
키인가요?
Is it key?
네, 좋습니다.
OK.
쿼리일까요?
Query?
좋아요.
OK.
여러분이 이 부분을 생각할 때,
So the way to think
about it is you're
입력에서 어떤 단어들이 중요한지 스스로 물어보는 겁니다.
trying to ask yourself, what are
the words from the input that
그게 핵심이죠.
matter.
맞죠?
Right?
즉, 주어진 쿼리에 대해
So basically, you
want know, given
입력에서 어떤 요소들이 중요한지를 알고 싶은 겁니다.
your query, what are the
elements from the inputs that
어떤 부분이 중요한지요.
matter?
그래서 여기서 이 화살표가 바로 쿼리를 의미합니다.
So here, this arrow
is indeed the query,
여기서 우리가 알아내고 싶은 것이 바로 이 쿼리이기 때문입니다.
because this is the thing
that you want to figure out.
그리고 키와 값은 사실
And the keys and
values are actually
인코더에서 오게 되죠, 즉
coming from the encoder,
which are basically
입력 시퀀스에서 나온다는 의미입니다.
coming from the input sequence.
그리고 여기에 또 하나의 어텐션 레이어가 있습니다.
And then you have
another attention layer,
바로 이것이죠.
which is this one.
그리고 이것은
And that one is
trying to figure out
디코딩 중인 출력 문장에서
어떤 토큰이 다음 토큰 예측에 도움이 될지
what other tokens of the output
sentence that you're decoding
즉, 다음 토큰을 예측하는 데 유용한
다른 토큰이 무엇인지 알아내려는 겁니다.
is going to be useful to
predict the next token.
예를 들어, 여러분이 디코딩을 시작하면서
So let's suppose
you start decoding
"un ours en peluche"라고 한다고 해봅시다. 프랑스어죠.
and you say, un ours en
peluche, which is in French.
다음 단어를 예측하려면,
To predict the next word, you
want to basically figure out
지금까지 번역한 토큰들 중에서
what are the tokens
translated so far that
다음 단어를 예측하는 데 어떤 토큰이 도움이 되는지를 파악해야 합니다.
are going to be useful
to predict the next word.
이것이 바로 이 어텐션 레이어가 하는 역할입니다.
So this is what this
attention layer is about.
이 레이어를 마스킹된(maksed) 어텐션이라고 부르는 이유는,
And it's called
masked, because it only
지금까지 번역된 토큰만을 보기 때문입니다.
looks at the tokens
that translated so far.
아직 번역되지 않은 토큰들은 참고하지 않습니다.
It does not look at
tokens that were not
당연히 번역되지 않은 부분은 볼 수 없기 때문입니다.
translated, because of course
they were not translated.
즉, 우리가 예측하려는 토큰의 오른쪽에 있는 토큰은 볼 수 없습니다.
So there's no way, like on
the right side of the token
지금 예측하려는 토큰 오른쪽은 접근할 수 없습니다.
that you're trying to predict.
좋습니다.
Cool.
자, 전체적으로 보면 어텐션 레이어가 인코더에도 있고 디코더에도 있습니다.
So at a very high level, you
have this attention layer,
이 어텐션 레이어는 인코더와 디코더 모두에 포함되어 있지만,
which is present in the encoder,
which is present in the decoder,
용도는 여러 가지로 나눌 수 있습니다.
but it has several,
I guess, use cases.
여기서 어텐션 레이어는 입력 문장의 임베딩을 계산하는 역할을 합니다.
So the attention layer here
aims at computing embeddings
임베딩을 각 토큰 자체를 함수로 삼아 계산하는 셈이죠.
from the input sentence as
a function of themselves.
그리고 디코더 쪽에서는,
And then the ones
from the decoder,
첫 번째로 마스킹된 셀프 어텐션 레이어는,
so the first one, the
masked self-attention layer,
지금까지 디코딩된 모든 정보를 함수로 표현하는 걸 목표로 합니다.
aims at expressing something as
a function of everything that
즉, 지금까지 디코딩된 정보를 바탕으로 표현합니다.
has been decoded so far.
두 번째로 크로스 어텐션 레이어는,
And the second one, the
cross-attention layer,
입력에서 본 내용을 함수로써 토큰을 표현합니다.
tries to express things
as a function of what
즉, 입력에서 확인한 정보를 바탕으로 표현하는 거죠.
has been seen in the input.
여기서 보면,
So here, given
that you are having
각기 다른 토큰들과 직접 연결할 수 있기 때문에,
direct links to
different tokens,
순서감이 사라집니다.
you don't have this
sense of order.
RNN의 경우에는,
Because in the RNN,
you are basically
각 토큰을 한 번에 하나씩 처리하니까 순서감이 있었습니다.
expressing things one at a time.
그래서 단어 순서에 대한 감각이 있었죠.
So you had some sense
of the word order,
하지만 트랜스포머에서는 이런 순서감이 없습니다.
but here you don't
have it, because it's
토큰 간에 직접 연결이 주어지기 때문이고, 그래서 위치 인코딩이 필요한 겁니다.
like a direct link, which
is why you have position
위치 인코딩은 각 단어가 시퀀스 내에서 어디에 있는지 정보를 제공합니다.
encodings, which
are there to inform
즉, 단어의 위치 정보를 모델에 알려주는 역할을 하죠.
on the position of the
word in the sequence.
그래서 오늘은 이 부분까지 깊게 들어가지는 않겠습니다.
So we're not going to
dig into that today,
다만 이런 부분이 있다는 점만 짚고 넘어가려는 겁니다.
but I just want
to call that out.
아주 상위 단계에서, 그리고 곧 자세한 예시에서도 보겠지만,
So at a very high
level, and we're
어떤 과정을 거치는지 차근차근 살펴볼 겁니다.
going to see this in the
detailed example, what
원문에서 목표 언어로 문장을 번역할 때,
we do is in order to translate
a sentence from source language
먼저 텍스트를 토큰화해서
to target language,
we're first going
텍스트를 임의의 단위, 즉 토큰으로 나눕니다.
to tokenize the text, so
dividing into arbitrary units.
이제 토큰별 임베딩을 학습하게 됩니다.
We're going to learn an
embedding for these tokens.
이게 바로 입력 임베딩(input embedding)에 해당하는 부분입니다.
So this is what the
input embedding is about.
그 다음에는 각각의 위치에 맞는 인코딩 정보를 추가해줍니다.
Then we're going to add
some encoding with respect
즉, 토큰의 위치 정보를 더해줍니다.
to the position.
이 부분도 오늘 자세히 다루지는 않지만, 중요하다는 점만 알아두면 됩니다.
We're not going to talk about
it today, but just good to note.
그리고 나서 인코더를 거치게 됩니다.
And then we go
through the encoder.
인코더는
So the encoder
tries to figure out
입력 안의 다른 요소들을 바탕으로
how to express things as
a function of other things
각각을 어떻게 표현할지 학습합니다.
from the inputs.
이 과정을 멀티헤드 어텐션 레이어에서 수행하게 됩니다.
So it does that in the
multi-head attention layer.
그리고 피드포워드 신경망(feedforward neural network)을 한번 더 통과합니다.
And then it goes through a
feedforward neural network,
이 단계는 벡터를 투영해서
which is just a way to just
project the vectors to just
모델이 더 유연하게 다양한 것을 배울 수 있게 해줍니다.
have some more degrees of
freedom to learn things.
이렇게 입력을 통해 얻은 표현이 나오면,
And then once you have these
representations from the input,
이제 본격적으로 번역을 시작하게 됩니다.
you're then going to
start your translation.
먼저 BOS 토큰으로 시작합니다.
So you start with the BOS token.
이제 우리가 해야 할 일은,
And what you're
trying to do is figure
다음 단어가 무엇인지 예측하는 것입니다.
out what the next word is.
지금까지 번역된 단어들을 보고,
So you're going to
see, OK, what are
번역 과정에 도움이 되는 단어들이 무엇인지
the words that were
translated so far that
확인하게 됩니다.
are useful for translation.
이 역할을 하는 것이 마스킹된 멀티헤드 어텐션 레이어입니다.
So this is what the masked
multi-head attention layer does.
그리고 또 한 번 어텐션 레이어가 뒤따릅니다.
And then you have
another attention layer,
이 레이어는 입력값에 따라 출력을 결정하는 역할을 합니다.
which is about expressing
things as a function of what
이게 바로 입력값을 활용하는 크로스 어텐션 레이어입니다.
was in the input, which is
the cross-attention layer
바로 저기 있는 레이어죠.
over there.
그리고 피드포워드 신경망이 한 번 더 들어가서
And then you have a feedforward
neural network to, again,
모델의 표현력을 더 높여줍니다.
give some more
degrees of freedom.
결국 마지막에는 하나의 벡터가 나오게 되고,
And at the end of the day, you
have a vector that you then
이 벡터가 소프트맥스를 거치게 됩니다.
go through softmax.
즉, 이 과정을 통해 다음에 올 단어를 예측하게 되는 거죠.
And it just is a way for you
to guess what is the next word.
출력 벡터의 차원은 어휘집 크기와 같습니다.
So you have a vector
of vocabulary size.
이 값들을 이용해서
And you're going to use
these values to determine
다음에 올 단어를 결정합니다.
what is your next word.
생각보다 간단하죠?
Easy, right?
여기까지 질문 있는 분 있나요?
Any questions on this?
네.
Yeah.
좋은 질문입니다.
All right, that's
a great question.
질문은 'head가 무엇인가요?'입니다.
The question is,
what does head mean?
제가 너무 빨리 넘어갔던 것 같네요.
So I guess I went too fast.
그 부분을 설명하지 않았습니다.
I ignored that part.
셀프 어텐션 연산을 할 때,
But when you do the
self-attention computation,
쿼리가 키와 상호작용하고
you basically make queries
interact with keys,
해당하는 값을 가져오게 됩니다.
and then take the
corresponding value.
이 과정을 여러 번 반복해도 문제는 없습니다.
But nothing prevents you from
doing that several times.
'head'라는 용어는 쿼리, 키, 값을 얻기 위해 사용하는
So the term "head" is given to
the projection matrices that you
투영 행렬을 의미합니다.
use to obtain the
query, key, and value.
여러 개의 head가 있으면,
And when you have several
heads, what you're doing
모델이 서로 다른 투영을 학습할 수 있게 됩니다.
is you're allowing your model
to learn different projections.
결국 이는 모델이 표현할 수 있는 자유도를
So it's basically
an additional degree
더 늘려주어 다양한 연관성을 학습하게 해줍니다.
of freedom for your model to
learn different associations
각 벡터 사이의 연관성을 여러 방식으로 학습하는 거죠.
between your vectors.
아주 좋은 질문이었습니다.
So it's a great question.
그래서 보통 소문자 h로 머리 수, 즉 head의 개수를 표시합니다.
So typically it will be noted
lowercase h, number of heads.
이게 바로 여기서 말하는 머리 수와 대응되는 부분입니다.
And this is what
this corresponds to.
이렇게 설명하면 궁금증이 해결되셨나요?
Does that answer your question?
좋아요, 아주 좋습니다.
Cool, very cool.
네, 이야기할 내용이 많지만, 여기에서
이 부분에 대한 슬라이드를 준비해뒀습니다.
OK, we have a lot to
discuss, but here I
실제로 이 내용을 설명하는 슬라이드입니다.
had the slide actually for this.
여기서 말씀하셨던 멀티헤드를 나타낸 것입니다.
So this is the multi-heads
that you were mentioning.
즉, 셀프 어텐션 연산을 한 번이 아니라
여러 번 병렬로 수행하는 셈입니다.
So we're basically running
the self-attention computation
다시 말해, 각각을 다른 프로젝션 행렬로
병렬 처리하게 되는 거죠.
several times in
parallel, again,
이 프로젝션 행렬은 모델이 학습합니다.
with different projection
matrices that the model learns.
혹시 컴퓨터 비전 쪽 배경이 있다면,
So in case you have a
computer vision background,
여러 개의 컨볼루션 필터를 사용하는 것과
비슷하다고 볼 수 있습니다.
it is similar to having multiple
filters in your convolution.
개념은 비슷하지만, 여기서는 방식이 다릅니다.
So it's the same idea,
but it's different here.
좋은 질문이었습니다.
Yeah, great question.
질문이, 각 프로젝션이 서로 다른가요? 였죠.
So the question is, are
the projections different?
보통은 이런 부분에 제약을 두지 않습니다.
So we're typically not
constraining things.
모델이 자유롭게 학습하게 두는 겁니다.
We're just letting
the model learn.
실제로는 같은 의미를 여러 방식으로
학습하는 경향이 있습니다.
But in practice, it just
tends to learn different ways
같은 말을 다르게 표현한다고 볼 수 있죠.
of saying the same thing.
그래서 보통 특별히 제약을 두지 않습니다.
So yeah, typically
there is no constraint.
물론, 이런 부분을 바꿨을 때 어떻게 되는지
다루는 논문들도 있습니다.
Of course, you have papers
that dig into how about
이 부분을 다르게 하면 어떻게 될지 연구한 거죠.
if you change this.
하지만 보통은 별도의 제약 없이 진행합니다.
But typically you don't
have any constraint.
좋아요, 아주 좋습니다.
Cool, great.
네, 여기서 한 가지 팁을 더 말씀드리면,
OK, I will just
mention one trick,
트랜스포머 논문에서 사용한 또다른 기법이 있습니다.
another trick that the
transformer authors use.
바로 레이블 스무딩(label smoothing)이라는 방법인데요.
So it's called label smoothing.
혹시 레이블 스무딩 들어보신 분 계신가요?
Who has heard of
label smoothing?
여기서 새롭게 도입되는 점은, NLP에서는 보통
So one new thing
here is in NLP when
다음에 올 토큰을 예측하려고 할 때,
you want to predict
what comes next,
다음에 올 단어를 예측할 때는
보통 여러 가지 정답이 존재합니다.
there's typically
more than one way.
예를 들어, 'What a great day',
'What a great...'
When you say, what
a great day, what
'What a great lecture', 'What a great book',
'What a great...'과 같이 이어질 수 있죠.
a great lecture, what a
great book, what a great--
이처럼 항상 여러 선택지가 있습니다.
there's always multiple choices.
그 빈칸을 채우는 방법이 한 가지가 아닌 거죠.
There's more than one
way of filling that gap.
그래서 레이블 스무딩(label smoothing)은
이런 점을 직관적으로 다루려는 기법입니다.
So label smoothing
is a technique
즉, 이러한 문제를
직접적으로 해결하려는 시도입니다.
that tries to
intuitively address that.
구체적으로는, 특정 단어를 100% 예측하라고
요구하는 대신,
And what it does is, instead of
saying predict this word 100%
'정답은 이것 하나뿐이다'라고 하지 않고,
이렇게 말해줍니다.
is this one, there is no other
words, what it does is it says,
'이 단어를 예측하되, 아닐 가능성도 있다'는 식이죠.
predict this word, but there's
a chance it's not this word.
실제로는 원-핫 인코딩을 사용해서,
And in practice, what it does is
it takes the one-hot encoding.
'1, 0, 0, 0' 형태로 정답을 주는 대신,
And instead of saying
it's a 1, 0, 0, 0,
'실제로는'이라고 하면서
that you need to predict,
it says it's actually
1-ε, 그리고 나머지는 ε/(v-1)로 할당합니다.
1 minus epsilon, and then
epsilon over v minus 1, I guess,
즉, 이렇게 분포를 예측하게 만드는 거죠.
is you're trying to predict.
실제로 이 방법은,
So in practice,
it's a method that
모델이 자신의 정답에 대해 덜 확신을 가지도록
만드는 효과가 있습니다.
tends to make your
model be more unsure.
즉, 예측에 대해
확신을 조금 줄여주는 거죠.
Again, to be less sure
about this prediction
항상 이렇게 알려주기 때문에,
'이걸 예측해봐, 하지만 진짜 정답이 아닐 수도 있어'라고요.
because you always tell it,
OK, try to predict this,
실제로는 정답이 아닐 확률도 있다고 알려주는 것입니다.
but actually it's possible
it's not the correct value.
그런데 실제로 논문 저자들은
But in practice, the
authors see that it
이 방법이 BLEU처럼 번역 과제에서
사용되는 평가 지표를 향상시키는 것을 관찰했습니다.
tends to improve
metrics like BLEU,
BLEU는 번역 작업에서 활용되는 평가 척도죠.
which is a proxy metric
for translation tasks.
그래서 이 방법은 NLP 분야에서
꽤 범용적으로 쓰인다고 볼 수 있습니다.
So yeah, I think this method
is pretty general for NLP.
즉, 알아두면 좋은 기법입니다.
So yeah, it's a
good one to know.
자, 이제 약 20분 정도 남았습니다.
And with that, I think there's
about 20-ish minutes left.
이제부터 Shervine이
엔드 투 엔드 예제를 함께 다뤄줄 것입니다.
So yeah, Shervine
is going to walk you
직접 처음부터 끝까지 예제를 진행해 줄 거예요.
through an end-to-end example.
이렇게 해서 여러분은...
And with that, you--
네, 아, 여러분?
yeah, Oh, u?
여기서는 이것을 어떤 값이라고 생각하시면 됩니다.
So I guess here you can think of
this as, I guess, some quantity.
정확히 정의되어 있진 않아서, 그냥 어떤 수치라고 보면 됩니다.
It's not defined,
so some quantity.
델타는 원한다면 one-hot처럼 표현할 수도 있습니다.
And the delta is like one
hot, if you want, something
이런 식으로요.
like this.
상수가 될 수도 있습니다.
It can also be a constant.
네, 맞아요.
Yeah, yeah.
질문이 있는데, 여기서 무언가 연관성이 있을까요?
So question is, is
there a relation
explore와 exploit과 관련이 있을까요?
with explore and exploit?
흥미로운 질문이네요.
It's an interesting one.
그렇다면 왜 소프트맥스는 이런 걸 그냥 제공한다고 할까요?
So why would softmax give
it for free, by the way?
맞아요, 그래도 여전히...
Right, but I guess
it would still--
결국 여러분이 하려는 건,
so I guess at the end
of the day, what you're
모델의 예측값을 라벨과 비교하는 것이죠.
trying to do is to compare
your prediction with respect
라벨을 기준으로 비교하는 겁니다.
to the label.
여기서 질문은, 여러분이
So I guess the question
here is, do you
1, 0, 0, 0과 비교할지,
want to compare with
1, 0, 0, 0, or do you
아니면 1, 0, 0, 0이 아닌 다른 값과 비교할지 입니다.
want to compare with something
that is not 1, 0, 0, 0.
소프트맥스는 이런 식의 비교를 허용하지 않습니다.
So I guess softmax does
not allow you to do that.
맞습니다, 그렇죠.
Exactly, yes.
이 부분이 충분히 명확했는지 모르겠지만,
So I'm not sure if
this was super clear,
사실 이게 라벨입니다.
but this is actually the label.
여러분이 예측하려는 건 1, 0, 0이 아니죠.
So what you're trying to
predict is not 1, 0, 0.
하지만 우리는 라벨을 변경해서
But we change the label in
a way that makes the model,
모델이 좀 더 확신이 덜한 값을 예측하게 만듭니다.
I guess, predict something
that is less sure, I guess.
좋아요, 감사합니다.
Cool, thanks.
자, 이제 Shervine이 이어 받겠습니다.
And with that, yeah, Shervine.
네, 좋습니다.
OK, great.
감사합니다, Afshine.
Thank you, Afshine.
네, 이제까지 트랜스포머가 어떻게 동작하는지 살펴봤습니다.
And yes, so we saw basically
how the transformer worked.
이제 하나의 예시로 전체를 연결해서 설명하겠습니다.
And now we're going to
piece it all together
하나의 구체적인 예시를 가지고 모두 정리해보겠습니다.
with the one specific example.
네, 좋습니다.
OK, great.
그러면 다시 우리가 좋아하는 예시를 들어보겠습니다.
So let's take our
favorite example again.
귀여운 곰인형이 책을 읽고 있습니다.
So a cute teddy bear is reading.
그리고 이제 각 단계를 함께 하나씩 따라가 볼게요.
And then we'll go all
together through each step.
먼저, 토큰화부터 시작합니다.
So first we start
with tokenization.
말씀드린 것처럼, 임의의 분할 방식을 사용할 수 있습니다.
So as we said, we can use
any arbitrary decomposition
이 문장을 토큰 단위로 쪼개는 것이죠.
to decompose this into tokens.
또 누군가 언급해줬듯이,
And then as someone
mentioned, you
시퀀스의 시작과 끝을 표시하는 방법이 필요합니다.
need to have some way to
indicate the start and the end
즉, 시퀀스의 처음과 마지막을 나타내야 하죠.
of a sequence.
그래서 일반적으로 BOS, EOS 토큰을 사용합니다.
So typically, this is done
with the BOS and EOS tokens.
이런 토큰들을 추가해줍니다.
So you add them.
이제 각 토큰의 구성에 집중해봅시다.
So now let's focus
on the composition
각 토큰 표현이 어떻게 만들어지는지 살펴보겠습니다.
of each token representation.
먼저 토큰마다 임베딩이 있습니다.
So you have its embedding.
이 임베딩은 학습을 통해 얻어집니다.
That is learned.
그리고 Afshine이 말한 것처럼,
And as Afshine
mentioned, in order
단어나 토큰의 위치 정보를 인식할 수 있도록
to have an idea of what is
the position of the words
문장 내에서 해당 토큰의 위치를 알 수 있게
or the token, I should say
as part of the sequence,
추가적인 정보가 포함됩니다.
you have some added
information that
이 정보는 위치 임베딩의 형태로 더해집니다.
is in the form of a
position embedding.
여기서 원래 논문에서는
And here, the original
paper uses the convention
사인 함수와 코사인 함수를 사용해
of some sines and cosines
that it adds additively
이 값을 토큰 표현에 가산합니다.
to the representation.
즉, 요소별로 값을 더하는 방식입니다.
So it's like an
element-wise addition.
네, 좋아요.
OK, great.
이제 각 토큰마다 위치 정보를 가진 임베딩이 생성됩니다.
So now you have a position-aware
embedding for your token.
그리고 이 작업을 모든 토큰에 반복합니다.
And you repeat that for
each of your tokens.
이제 이렇게 만든 임베딩 전체를 볼 수 있습니다.
So now you can see all
of these embeddings
이제 이 임베딩들을 행렬 형태로 볼 수 있는데,
이 행렬의 크기는 d_model입니다.
in the format of a matrix,
which is of size d model, which
여기서 d_model은 임베딩의 차원입니다.
is the size of your embeddings.
다른 한 축은 시퀀스의 길이인데,
And then the other
dimension is the length
보통 n으로 표시합니다.
of the sequence, so typically n.
여기까지 괜찮으신가요?
So all make sense so far?
입력에 대해 질문 있으신가요?
Any questions on the inputs?
네, 좋습니다.
OK, great.
그럼 이제 이 표현을
So now we will send
this representation
인코더에 넣어보겠습니다.
through the encoder.
앞서 Afshine이 말했듯이,
여기에는 셀프 어텐션 개념이 있습니다.
So as Afshine said, you have
this concept of self-attention.
셀프 어텐션을 수행하는 방식은
And the way you
perform self-attention
이 입력을 세 가지 공간으로 투영하는 것입니다.
is that you take this input
and project it on three spaces.
먼저 Wq 공간으로 투영하면 쿼리가 되고,
So you project it to the
space Wq, you get queries.
같은 임베딩을 Wk 공간으로 투영하면 키가 됩니다.
You project the same embeddings
in the space Wk, you get keys.
값도 마찬가지로 투영해서 값을 얻습니다.
And you do the same for
values, you get your values.
이때 Wq, Wk, Wv 행렬은 모두 모델이 학습합니다.
And then Wq, Wk, and Wv
are learned by the model.
이 행렬들은 기본적으로 투영 행렬입니다.
They are basically
projection matrices.
여기까지 괜찮으신가요?
So far, so good?
이제 이 모든 내용을 바탕으로,
So now with all of
that in mind, you
Afshine이 알려준 공식을 적용할 수 있습니다.
can apply the formula
that Afshine mentioned,
즉, 셀프 어텐션 공식이죠.
that is the
self-attention formula,
소프트맥스(Q와 K의 전치행렬을 곱하고,
dk의 제곱근으로 나누는 것)입니다.
which is softmax of Qk
transpose over square root of dk
여기에 v를 곱하면,
이 전체로부터 또 다른 행렬이 만들어집니다.
times v, which gives you another
matrix out of all of this.
여기서 잠시 멈추고,
Now let's pause for
a second and look
실제로 이 계산이 어떻게 이루어지는지,
at how this computation
is done in practice
각 단계가 무엇을 의미하는지 살펴보겠습니다.
and what every step means.
그럼 Q를 한번 살펴볼까요?
Q를 계산할 때는,
So let's look at Q.
When you compute Q,
임베딩을 해당 공간에 투영하게 됩니다.
basically you project your
embeddings into that space.
이때 어떤 결과가 나올까요?
What do you obtain?
각 행이 각각의 쿼리를 나타내는
행렬이 나오게 됩니다.
You obtain a matrix where each
row represents a given query.
K의 전치, 즉 transpose를 하면
원래 행렬을 전치시키는 것입니다.
When you say k
transpose, it's basically
같은 행렬이지만, 전치시킨 것이죠.
여기서는
the same matrix, but
transposed, where
각 열이 각 토큰의 key 표현을 나타내게 됩니다.
each column represents the key
representation of each token.
이제 행렬 곱을 통해
두 값을 섞어주겠습니다.
Now let's mix them together
with the matrix multiplication.
이렇게 각각을 곱해주면,
So when you multiply
each of them,
각 행은 쿼리가
you see that each row
represents the projection
각 key에 대해 어떻게 투영되는지를 나타냅니다.
즉, 행렬 곱을 이용하면
of the query over each key, such
that when you take the matrix
그 결과에 소프트맥스를 적용해서
multiplication and get the
softmax of all of this,
확률 분포를 얻게 됩니다.
you get a probability
distribution
각 쿼리에 대해 key에 대한 투영이
확률 분포 형태로 나옵니다.
of the projection of the query
over keys for each query.
각 행마다 이러한 결과가 담깁니다.
Each line will have this.
그리고 혹시, 왜 sqrt(dk)로 나누는지
궁금해한 분 계실지 모르겠는데요,
And I don't know if anyone asked
the question regarding why do we
왜 key 차원의 제곱근으로 스케일링하는지
질문이 나올 수 있습니다.
scale by square root of dk?
사실 dq로 나누어도 되는데,
행렬 곱,
So it could be dq as well
because matrix multiplication,
여기서 내적(dot product)이
like the dot product
here, enforces
사실 dq와 dk가 같다는 걸 전제로 하고 있기 때문입니다.
the fact that dq equals dk.
그리고 이런 내적값들은
And basically, what you see
is that these dot products has
key와 query 차원이 커질수록
값이 커질 수 있습니다.
the dimension of key
and queries grows,
즉, 차원이 커지면 내적값도 함께 커집니다.
it will tend to grow as well.
그래서 이런 내적값을 정규화해야 합니다.
So you want to normalize
these dot products.
이 때문에 key 차원의 제곱근으로 나누는 것입니다.
And this is why you
divide by square root
즉, key의 차원만큼 루트로 나눠줍니다.
of the dimension of keys.
네, 좋습니다.
OK, great.
이제 이렇게 소프트맥스까지 구했으면,
And then now you have your
softmax of all of these,
여기에 v 행렬을 곱합니다.
and then you multiply
it with the matrix
Afshine이 설명한 대로, 쿼리를 key의 공간에 투영하고,
v. And this is Afshine explained
as having the query projected
그 다음에 해당 값(value)과 곱해주는 것입니다.
on the space of keys,
and then multiplied
즉, 해당하는 value를 곱해서
by the corresponding value.
value는 그 key가 가진 표현을 나타냅니다.
So the value is
the representation
즉, 우리가 투영한 key에 해당하는
값의 표현을 의미합니다.
of the corresponding
key that we project on.
그래서 결국 각 쿼리에 대해
가중합된 value들의 합이 나옵니다.
So you end up with a weighted
sum of values for each query.
네, 좋습니다.
OK, great.
여기까지 이해되셨나요?
Does that make sense so far?
네, 아주 좋습니다.
OK, awesome.
그리고 누군가 멀티헤드가 뭔지 질문했는데요.
And someone asked, what
is the multi-head stuff?
맞아요, 이게 한 번만 하는 게 아니고
So you're right, it's not
just single one, one time
여러 번 반복해서 수행합니다.
that it's done.
사실 여러 번 각각 수행하는 거죠.
It's actually done each times.
그리고 이런 과정이
모두 병렬로 일어납니다.
And what you obtain is, like,
all of that is done in parallel.
결국 h개의 행렬을 얻게 되고요.
And at the end, you
obtain h such matrices.
이 행렬들을 열 방향으로 이어 붙입니다.
And you concatenate them
with respect to the columns.
이렇게 해서 마지막에는
프로젝션 행렬이 하나 더 있습니다.
And at the end of this, you
have another projection matrix
이 행렬을 Wo라고 하는데,
이게 모든 결과를 다시
that you call Wo that will
project all of these back
원래 임베딩 차원으로
되돌려주는 역할을 합니다.
to the original
dimension of embeddings.
즉, 신경망이 기본적으로
차원에 구애받지 않고
So it's a way for the
network to basically have
처리하는 방식이라고 볼 수 있습니다.
a dimension-invariant way--
에취! 원래 차원에서 다시
bless you-- to go from
the original dimension
원래 임베딩 차원으로 돌아가는 거죠.
back to the original one.
질문 있으신가요?
Any questions?
네.
Yep.
질문은 h에 관한 것이군요.
So the question is regarding h.
매번 같은 결과가 나올 수도 있나요?
Is it possible to get the
same result each time?
만약 그렇다면, 이걸 이어 붙였을 때
실제로 도움이 될까요?
And if so, concatenate the
same thing, will it be helpful?
제 질문 이해가 맞았나요?
Did I get the question right?
그럼 무엇이 다르게 만드는 걸까요?
So what makes it different?
이건 바로 경사하강법의 마법입니다.
So it's the magic
of gradient descent.
신경망은 마지막에 목적 함수를 가지고 있습니다.
So the network has an
objective function at the end.
여기에는 여러 자유도가 존재하죠.
It has degrees of freedom.
이 신경망의 목표는 다음 단어를
예측하는 데 도움이 되는
Its incentive is to build a
representation that will be
유용한 표현을 만들도록 유도받아요.
helpful to learn the next word.
그래서 모델은 같은 것을 복사하거나
So it doesn't have an incentive
to copy the same thing
같은 메커니즘을 반복할 동기가 없습니다.
or do the same mechanism.
그래서 실제로 보면 모델이 서로 다른 표현을 학습하도록
And this is why in practice
you see the model converge
수렴하는 모습을 볼 수 있습니다.
towards building different
representations that it can then
이렇게 학습된 표현들을 합치고,
concatenate and then project
into something useful.
그것을 유용하게 활용할 수 있도록 투영하게 됩니다.
So what makes it such that
you don't have the same thing?
그렇다면 왜 같은 것이 반복되지 않을까요?
Nothing.
사실 아무런 제약이 없습니다.
Like, you don't have
any constraints.
네, 모델에 제약을 둔 건 없지만,
But the nature of the learning
that you let the model have
실제로는 학습 방식 때문에 이런 결과가 나타납니다.
makes it do so in practice.
다른 질문 있으신가요?
Any other questions?
아주 좋은 질문이었습니다.
And that is a great question.
사실, 경사하강법은 대부분의 경우 굉장히 놀라운 결과를 보여줍니다.
I mean, typically gradient
descent does wonders.
좋습니다.
OK great.
이제 셀프 어텐션 레이어를 살펴봤으니,
So now that we have gone through
the self-attention layer,
다른 구성 요소인 FFN에 대해 알아보겠습니다.
you have another
component that is the FFN.
여기에서 은닉 레이어의 차원을 어떻게 정하는지에 대해
And I think there was a
question just here regarding
질문이 있었던 것 같습니다.
how to choose the dimension
of the hidden layer
입력과 출력에 따라 은닉 레이어의 차원을
with respect to the
input and outputs.
어떻게 정하는지에 관한 내용인데요,
So when Afshine
mentioned Word2vec,
Afshine이 Word2vec을 언급했을 때 보통은
typically you have
a smaller dimension
은닉 차원이 입력과 출력보다 작습니다.
than the input and output.
하지만 여기서는 실제로 은닉 레이어의 차원이
But here, actually,
the hidden layer
입력이나 출력보다 더 큽니다.
is of a bigger dimension
than input and output.
이런 구조를 택하는 이유는,
And the rationale
for that is that you
모델이 유용한 표현을 학습할 수 있도록
want to have enough degrees of
freedom for the model to learn
충분한 자유도를 확보하기 위함입니다.
useful representations.
즉, 학습되는 특징을 더 복잡하게 만들기 위한 방법이죠.
So it's a way to complexify
the features that you learn.
네, 그렇습니다.
And, yeah [INAUDIBLE].
좋아요.
OK, great.
그리고 인코더 모듈이 하나만 있는 것이 아닙니다.
And you don't have just
one encoder module.
실제로는 n개의 인코더, 즉 원 논문에서 말하는 대문자 N개가 있습니다.
You have actually n of them,
big N in the original paper.
그리고 이 모든 과정을 거치면
And at the end of
all of this, you
컨텍스트 정보를 담은 인코딩된 임베딩 집합을 얻게 됩니다.
have an encoded context-aware
set of embeddings.
그리고 각각의 인코딩된 임베딩은
And then each of
these setups encoded
n개의 디코더에 입력으로 들어가게 됩니다.
embeddings will be those that
will be fed to the n decoders.
이렇게 n개의 인코더가 층을 이루듯 쌓여 있습니다.
So you have like a stacked
succession of n encoders.
마찬가지로 n개의 디코더도 층을 이루며 쌓여 있습니다.
You have a stacked
succession of n decoders.
그리고 인코더의 마지막 표현이
And the last representation
of the encoder
각 디코더의 크로스 어텐션에 입력으로 들어갑니다.
is what you will feed to the
cross-attention of each decoder.
이 부분은 곧 더 자세히 살펴보겠습니다.
So yeah, we're going to
see that more in detail.
그럼 디코딩 과정은 어떻게 시작될까요?
So how do we even start
the decoding process?
먼저 BOS 토큰으로 시작합니다.
So you start with the BOS token.
즉, 모델에게 이제 시작하라는 신호를 보내는 거죠.
Basically saying to
the model, hey, we
다음 단어를 예측해야 하니 시작하라는 의미입니다.
need to predict the
next word, let's start.
그렇다면 맨 처음의 BOS 토큰은 어떻게 처리될까요?
So what happens to the BOS
token at the very beginning?
이 토큰을 디코더에 입력으로 넣어줍니다.
So you feed it to the decoder.
그리고 인코더에서 했던 것처럼,
And then similarly as
before for the encoder,
여기에도 셀프 어텐션 레이어가 있습니다.
you have a self-attention layer.
Afshine이 언급한 것처럼, 디코더의 셀프 어텐션 레이어는 인과형입니다.
And as Afshine mentioned, the
self-attention layer is causal.
따라서 어텐션은 현재 토큰과
So the attention will be
done on the same token
그 이전의 토큰들에만 적용됩니다.
and the tokens that precede it.
그래서 첫 번째 BOS 토큰에는 차이가 없고,
So on this first BOS token,
you don't see a difference,
그냥 자기 자신에게만 어텐션을 하게 됩니다.
because it will just
attend to itself.
하지만 이후 토큰들을 디코딩할 때는,
But when you have other tokens
that you want to decode,
디코더가 어텐션을 적용하는 범위에 차이가 생깁니다.
you will have this
difference in where you
즉, 디코더가 어디에 어텐션을 주는지가 달라지죠.
attend with respect to decoder.
네, 좋습니다. 이렇게 셀프 어텐션 레이어를 통과하게 됩니다.
OK, great, goes through
the self-attention layer.
그리고 이미 언급했던
And then you have
what I mentioned
크로스 어텐션이 이어지는데, 이때 키와 값으로는
to be the cross-attention
that takes as keys and values
이렇게 인코딩된 임베딩이 입력으로 들어갑니다.
these encoded
embeddings as inputs.
그리고 쿼리는 셀프 어텐션 레이어를 통과한 값이 사용됩니다.
And then the queries
are those that come out
즉, 셀프 어텐션 레이어에서 나온 값들이 쿼리로 쓰입니다.
of the self-attention layer.
좋습니다.
OK, great.
그리고 나서 이 크로스 어텐션을 거치게 되죠.
And then once you do
this cross-attention,
그러면 인코더에서처럼
you have, just like
in the encoder,
FFN 컴포넌트를 통해 표현을 더욱 풍부하게 만듭니다.
an FFN component that makes
the representation richer.
혹시 질문 있나요?
Was there a question there?
아니요.
No.
그리고 마지막 단계에서, 이 모든 과정을 n번 반복하게 됩니다.
And then at the very end, so
you do all of that n times.
디코딩 과정의 맨 마지막에는
And at the very end of
the decoding process,
선형 프로젝션과 소프트맥스 레이어를 거쳐
you have a linear projection
and a softmax layer
다음 단어를 예측하게 되고,
to turn the prediction
of the next word
이를 어휘집 전체에 대한 확률분포로 변환합니다.
into a probability distribution
over the vocabulary.
좋습니다.
OK, great.
이렇게 해서 다음 단어를 예측하는 방식을 살펴봤습니다.
So we saw how to do that
for the next word here.
그리고 이 과정을 계속 반복합니다.
And basically you do
that again and again.
이렇게 해서 다음 토큰을 찾고,
So you have found
your next token,
사실상 원-핫 인코딩 형태로
which is like a
one-hot basically
원하는 내용을 표현하게 됩니다.
encoding of what you want.
그 임베딩을 다시 가져와서
And then you take that
embedding and then put it back
디코더에 넣고, 이 과정을 계속 반복합니다.
in the decoder and
continue this process.
언제 멈춰야 할까요?
And when do you stop?
이건 여러분께 드리는 질문입니다.
It's a question for you all.
EOS 토큰에 도달하면 멈춥니다.
When you hit the EOS token.
네, 맞습니다.
Yeah, yeah exactly.
좋아요.
OK, great.
이런 방식으로
And with this process,
it's basically
바로 이 오리지널 논문의 저자들이
how the authors of this
original landmark paper
기계번역을 구현했던 겁니다.
did machine translation.
그래서 이것이 바로 이 논문에서 제시된 대표적인 사용 사례입니다.
So this is typically the
use case that was presented.
질문 있나요?
Any questions?
좋습니다.
OK, awesome.
이것으로 강의를 마치겠습니다.
경청해 주셔서 감사합니다.
And with that, thank
you for your attention.
[박수]
[APPLAUSE]